Contributor List

More than 100 sharp-eyed and thoughtful readers have sent in suggestions and corrections over the past few years. Their contributions, and enthusiasm for this project, have been a huge help.

If you have a suggestion or correction, please send email to feedback@thinkpython.com. If I make a change based on your feedback, I will add you to the contributor list (unless you ask to be omitted).

If you include at least part of the sentence the error appears in, that makes it easy for me to search. Page and section numbers are fine, too, but not quite as easy to work with. Thanks!

Lloyd Hugh Allen sent in a correction to Section 8.4.
Yvon Boulianne sent in a correction of a semantic error in Chapter 5.
Fred Bremmer submitted a correction in Section 2.1.
Jonah Cohen wrote the Perl scripts to convert the LaTeX source for this book into beautiful HTML.
Michael Conlon sent in a grammar correction in Chapter 2 and an improvement in style in Chapter 1, and he initiated discussion on the technical aspects of interpreters.
Benoit Girard sent in a correction to a humorous mistake in Section 5.6.
Courtney Gleason and Katherine Smith wrote horsebet.py, which was used as a case study in an earlier version of the book. Their program can now be found on the website.
Lee Harr submitted more corrections than we have room to list here, and indeed he should be listed as one of the principal editors of the text.
James Kaylin is a student using the text. He has submitted numerous corrections.
David Kershaw fixed the broken catTwice function in Section 3.10.
Eddie Lam has sent in numerous corrections to Chapters 1, 2, and 3. He also fixed the Makefile so that it creates an index the first time it is run and helped us set up a versioning scheme.
Man-Yong Lee sent in a correction to the example code in Section 2.4.
David Mayo pointed out that the word “unconsciously" in Chapter 1 needed to be changed to “subconsciously".
Chris McAloon sent in several corrections to Sections 3.9 and 3.10.
Matthew J. Moelter has been a long-time contributor who sent in numerous corrections and suggestions to the book.
Simon Dicon Montford reported a missing function definition and several typos in Chapter 3. He also found errors in the increment function in Chapter 13.
John Ouzts corrected the definition of “return value" in Chapter 3.
Kevin Parks sent in valuable comments and suggestions as to how to improve the distribution of the book.
David Pool sent in a typo in the glossary of Chapter 1, as well as kind words of encouragement.
Michael Schmitt sent in a correction to the chapter on files and exceptions.
Robin Shaw pointed out an error in Section 13.1, where the printTime function was used in an example without being defined.
Paul Sleigh found an error in Chapter 7 and a bug in Jonah Cohen’s Perl script that generates HTML from LaTeX.
Craig T. Snydal is testing the text in a course at Drew University. He has contributed several valuable suggestions and corrections.
Ian Thomas and his students are using the text in a programming course. They are the first ones to test the chapters in the latter half of the book, and they have made numerous corrections and suggestions.
Keith Verheyden sent in a correction in Chapter 3.
Peter Winstanley let us know about a longstanding error in our Latin in Chapter 3.
Chris Wrobel made corrections to the code in the chapter on file I/O and exceptions.
Moshe Zadka has made invaluable contributions to this project. In addition to writing the first draft of the chapter on Dictionaries, he provided continual guidance in the early stages of the book.
Christoph Zwerschke sent several corrections and pedagogic suggestions, and explained the difference between gleich and selbe.
James Mayer sent us a whole slew of spelling and typographical errors, including two in the contributor list.
Hayden McAfee caught a potentially confusing inconsistency between two examples.
Angel Arnal is part of an international team of translators working on the Spanish version of the text. He has also found several errors in the English version.
Tauhidul Hoque and Lex Berezhny created the illustrations in Chapter 1 and improved many of the other illustrations.
Dr. Michele Alzetta caught an error in Chapter 8 and sent some interesting pedagogic comments and suggestions about Fibonacci and Old Maid.
Andy Mitchell caught a typo in Chapter 1 and a broken example in Chapter 2.
Kalin Harvey suggested a clarification in Chapter 7 and caught some typos.
Christopher P. Smith caught several typos and helped us update the book for Python 2.2.
David Hutchins caught a typo in the Foreword.
Gregor Lingl is teaching Python at a high school in Vienna, Austria. He is working on a German translation of the book, and he caught a couple of bad errors in Chapter 5.
Julie Peters caught a typo in the Preface.
Florin Oprina sent in an improvement in makeTime, a correction in printTime, and a nice typo.
D. J. Webre suggested a clarification in Chapter 3.
Ken found a fistful of errors in Chapters 8, 9 and 11.
Ivo Wever caught a typo in Chapter 5 and suggested a clarification in Chapter 3.
Curtis Yanko suggested a clarification in Chapter 2.
Ben Logan sent in a number of typos and problems with translating the book into HTML.
Jason Armstrong saw the missing word in Chapter 2.
Louis Cordier noticed a spot in Chapter 16 where the code didn’t match the text.
Brian Cain suggested several clarifications in Chapters 2 and 3.
Rob Black sent in a passel of corrections, including some changes for Python 2.2.
Jean-Philippe Rey at Ecole Centrale Paris sent a number of patches, including some updates for Python 2.2 and other thoughtful improvements.
Jason Mader at George Washington University made a number of useful suggestions and corrections.
Jan Gundtofte-Bruun reminded us that “a error” is an error.
Abel David and Alexis Dinno reminded us that the plural of “matrix” is “matrices”, not “matrixes”. This error was in the book for years, but two readers with the same initials reported it on the same day. Weird.
Charles Thayer encouraged us to get rid of the semi-colons we had put at the ends of some statements and to clean up our use of “argument” and “parameter”.
Roger Sperberg pointed out a twisted piece of logic in Chapter 3.
Sam Bull pointed out a confusing paragraph in Chapter 2.
Andrew Cheung pointed out two instances of “use before def.”
C. Corey Capel spotted the missing word in the Third Theorem of Debugging and a typo in Chapter 4.
Alessandra helped clear up some Turtle confusion.
Wim Champagne found a brain-o in a dictionary example.
Douglas Wright pointed out a problem with floor division in arc.
Jared Spindor found some jetsam at the end of a sentence.
Lin Peiheng sent a number of very helpful suggestions.
Ray Hagtvedt sent in two errors and a not-quite-error.
Torsten Hübsch pointed out an inconsistency in Swampy.
Inga Petuhhov corrected an example in Chapter 14.
Arne Babenhauserheide sent several helpful corrections.
Mark E. Casida is is good at spotting repeated words.
Scott Tyler filled in a that was missing. And then sent in a heap of corrections.
Gordon Shephard sent in several corrections, all in separate emails.
Andrew Turner spotted an error in Chapter 8.
Adam Hobart fixed a problem with floor division in arc.
Daryl Hammond and Sarah Zimmerman pointed out that I served up math.pi too early. And Zim spotted a typo.
George Sass found a bug in a Debugging section.
Brian Bingham suggested Exercise 11.9.
Leah Engelbert-Fenton pointed out that I used tuple as a variable name, contrary to my own advice. And then found a bunch of typos and a “use before def.”
Joe Funke spotted a typo.
Chao-chao Chen found an inconsistency in the Fibonacci example.
Jeff Paine knows the difference between space and spam.
Lubos Pintes sent in a typo.
Gregg Lind and Abigail Heithoff suggested Exercise 14.6.
Max Hailperin has sent in a number of corrections and suggestions. Max is one of the authors of the extraordinary Concrete Abstractions, which you might want to read when you are done with this book.
Chotipat Pornavalai found an error in an error message.
Stanislaw Antol sent a list of very helpful suggestions.
Eric Pashman sent a number of corrections for Chapters 4–11.
Miguel Azevedo found some typos.
Jianhua Liu sent in a long list of corrections.
Nick King found a missing word.
Martin Zuther sent a long list of suggestions.
Adam Zimmerman found an inconsistency in my instance of an “instance” and several other errors.
Ratnakar Tiwari suggested a footnote explaining degenerate triangles.
Anurag Goel suggested another solution for is_abecedarian and sent some additional corrections. And he knows how to spell Jane Austen.
Kelli Kratzer spotted one of the typos.
Mark Griffiths pointed out a confusing example in Chapter 3.
Roydan Ongie found an error in my Newton’s method.
Patryk Wolowiec helped me with a problem in the HTML version.
Mark Chonofsky told me about a new keyword in Python 3.0.
Russell Coleman helped me with my geometry.
Wei Huang spotted several typographical errors.
Karen Barber spotted the the oldest typo in the book.
Nam Nguyen found a typo and pointed out that I used the Decorator pattern but didn’t mention it by name.
Stéphane Morin sent in several corrections and suggestions.
Paul Stoop corrected a typo in uses_only.
Eric Bronner pointed out a confusion in the discussion of the order of operations.
Alexandros Gezerlis set a new standard for the number and quality of suggestions he submitted. We are deeply grateful!
Gray Thomas knows his right from his left.
Giovanni Escobar Sosa sent a long list of corrections and suggestions.
Alix Etienne fixed one of the URLs.
Kuang He found a typo.
Daniel Neilson corrected an error about the order of operations.
Will McGinnis pointed out that polyline was defined differently in two places.
Swarup Sahoo spotted a missing semi-colon.
Frank Hecker pointed out an exercise that was under-specified, and some broken links.
Animesh B helped me clean up a confusing example.

1.2  What is a program?

A program is a sequence of instructions that specifies how to perform a computation. The computation might be something mathematical, such as solving a system of equations or finding the roots of a polynomial, but it can also be a symbolic computation, such as searching and replacing text in a document or (strangely enough) compiling a program.

The details look different in different languages, but a few basic instructions appear in just about every language:

input:
Get data from the keyboard, a file, or some other device.
output:
Display data on the screen or send data to a file or other device.
math:
Perform basic mathematical operations like addition and multiplication.
conditional execution:
Check for certain conditions and execute the appropriate sequence of statements.
repetition:
Perform some action repeatedly, usually with some variation.

Believe it or not, that’s pretty much all there is to it. Every program you’ve ever used, no matter how complicated, is made up of instructions that look pretty much like these. So you can think of programming as the process of breaking a large, complex task into smaller and smaller subtasks until the subtasks are simple enough to be performed with one of these basic instructions.

That may be a little vague, but we will come back to this topic when we talk about algorithms.

1.3  What is debugging?

Programming is error-prone. For whimsical reasons, programming errors are called bugs and the process of tracking them down is called debugging.

Three kinds of errors can occur in a program: syntax errors, runtime errors, and semantic errors. It is useful to distinguish between them in order to track them down more quickly.

1.3.1  Syntax errors

Python can only execute a program if the syntax is correct; otherwise, the interpreter displays an error message. Syntax refers to the structure of a program and the rules about that structure. For example, parentheses have to come in matching pairs, so (1 + 2) is legal, but 8) is a syntax error.

In English readers can tolerate most syntax errors, which is why we can read the poetry of e. e. cummings without spewing error messages. Python is not so forgiving. If there is a single syntax error anywhere in your program, Python will display an error message and quit, and you will not be able to run your program. During the first few weeks of your programming career, you will probably spend a lot of time tracking down syntax errors. As you gain experience, you will make fewer errors and find them faster.

1.3.2  Runtime errors

The second type of error is a runtime error, so called because the error does not appear until after the program has started running. These errors are also called exceptions because they usually indicate that something exceptional (and bad) has happened.

Runtime errors are rare in the simple programs you will see in the first few chapters, so it might be a while before you encounter one.

1.3.3  Semantic errors

The third type of error is the semantic error. If there is a semantic error in your program, it will run successfully in the sense that the computer will not generate any error messages, but it will not do the right thing. It will do something else. Specifically, it will do what you told it to do.

The problem is that the program you wrote is not the program you wanted to write. The meaning of the program (its semantics) is wrong. Identifying semantic errors can be tricky because it requires you to work backward by looking at the output of the program and trying to figure out what it is doing.

1.3.4  Experimental debugging

One of the most important skills you will acquire is debugging. Although it can be frustrating, debugging is one of the most intellectually rich, challenging, and interesting parts of programming.

In some ways, debugging is like detective work. You are confronted with clues, and you have to infer the processes and events that led to the results you see.

Debugging is also like an experimental science. Once you have an idea about what is going wrong, you modify your program and try again. If your hypothesis was correct, then you can predict the result of the modification, and you take a step closer to a working program. If your hypothesis was wrong, you have to come up with a new one. As Sherlock Holmes pointed out, “When you have eliminated the impossible, whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.” (A. Conan Doyle, The Sign of Four)

For some people, programming and debugging are the same thing. That is, programming is the process of gradually debugging a program until it does what you want. The idea is that you should start with a program that does something and make small modifications, debugging them as you go, so that you always have a working program.

For example, Linux is an operating system that contains thousands of lines of code, but it started out as a simple program Linus Torvalds used to explore the Intel 80386 chip. According to Larry Greenfield, “One of Linus’s earlier projects was a program that would switch between printing AAAA and BBBB. This later evolved to Linux.” (The Linux Users’ Guide Beta Version 1).

Later chapters will make more suggestions about debugging and other programming practices.

1.4  Formal and natural languages

Natural languages are the languages people speak, such as English, Spanish, and French. They were not designed by people (although people try to impose some order on them); they evolved naturally.

Formal languages are languages that are designed by people for specific applications. For example, the notation that mathematicians use is a formal language that is particularly good at denoting relationships among numbers and symbols. Chemists use a formal language to represent the chemical structure of molecules. And most importantly:

Programming languages are formal languages that have been designed to express computations.

Formal languages tend to have strict rules about syntax. For example, 3 + 3 = 6 is a syntactically correct mathematical statement, but 3 + = 3 $ 6 is not. H2O is a syntactically correct chemical formula, but 2Zz is not.

Syntax rules come in two flavors, pertaining to tokens and structure. Tokens are the basic elements of the language, such as words, numbers, and chemical elements. One of the problems with 3 + = 3 $ 6 is that $ is not a legal token in mathematics (at least as far as I know). Similarly, 2Zz is not legal because there is no element with the abbreviation Zz.

The second type of syntax error pertains to the structure of a statement; that is, the way the tokens are arranged. The statement 3 + = 3 $ 6 is illegal because even though + and = are legal tokens, you can’t have one right after the other. Similarly, in a chemical formula the subscript comes after the element name, not before.

Exercise 1   Write a well-structured English sentence with invalid tokens in it. Then write another sentence with all valid tokens but with invalid structure.

When you read a sentence in English or a statement in a formal language, you have to figure out what the structure of the sentence is (although in a natural language you do this subconsciously). This process is called parsing.

For example, when you hear the sentence, “The penny dropped,” you understand that “the penny” is the subject and “dropped” is the predicate. Once you have parsed a sentence, you can figure out what it means, or the semantics of the sentence. Assuming that you know what a penny is and what it means to drop, you will understand the general implication of this sentence.

Although formal and natural languages have many features in common—tokens, structure, syntax, and semantics—there are some differences:

ambiguity:
Natural languages are full of ambiguity, which people deal with by using contextual clues and other information. Formal languages are designed to be nearly or completely unambiguous, which means that any statement has exactly one meaning, regardless of context.
redundancy:
In order to make up for ambiguity and reduce misunderstandings, natural languages employ lots of redundancy. As a result, they are often verbose. Formal languages are less redundant and more concise.
literalness:
Natural languages are full of idiom and metaphor. If I say, “The penny dropped,” there is probably no penny and nothing dropping1. Formal languages mean exactly what they say.

People who grow up speaking a natural language—everyone—often have a hard time adjusting to formal languages. In some ways, the difference between formal and natural language is like the difference between poetry and prose, but more so:

Poetry:
Words are used for their sounds as well as for their meaning, and the whole poem together creates an effect or emotional response. Ambiguity is not only common but often deliberate.
Prose:
The literal meaning of words is more important, and the structure contributes more meaning. Prose is more amenable to analysis than poetry but still often ambiguous.
Programs:
The meaning of a computer program is unambiguous and literal, and can be understood entirely by analysis of the tokens and structure.

Here are some suggestions for reading programs (and other formal languages). First, remember that formal languages are much more dense than natural languages, so it takes longer to read them. Also, the structure is very important, so it is usually not a good idea to read from top to bottom, left to right. Instead, learn to parse the program in your head, identifying the tokens and interpreting the structure. Finally, the details matter. Small errors in spelling and punctuation, which you can get away with in natural languages, can make a big difference in a formal language.

1.6  Debugging

It is a good idea to read this book in front of a computer so you can try out the examples as you go. You can run most of the examples in interactive mode, but if you put the code into a script, it is easier to try out variations.

Whenever you are experimenting with a new feature, you should try to make mistakes. For example, in the “Hello, world!” program, what happens if you leave out one of the quotation marks? What if you leave out both? What if you spell print wrong?

This kind of experiment helps you remember what you read; it also helps with debugging, because you get to know what the error messages mean. It is better to make mistakes now and on purpose than later and accidentally.

Programming, and especially debugging, sometimes brings out strong emotions. If you are struggling with a difficult bug, you might feel angry, despondent or embarrassed.

There is evidence that people naturally respond to computers as if they were people3. When they work well, we think of them as teammates, and when they are obstinate or rude, we respond to them the same way we respond to rude, obstinate people.

Preparing for these reactions might help you deal with them. One approach is to think of the computer as an employee with certain strengths, like speed and precision, and particular weaknesses, like lack of empathy and inability to grasp the big picture.

Your job is to be a good manager: find ways to take advantage of the strengths and mitigate the weaknesses. And find ways to use your emotions to engage with the problem, without letting your reactions interfere with your ability to work effectively.

Learning to debug can be frustrating, but it is a valuable skill that is useful for many activities beyond programming. At the end of each chapter there is a debugging section, like this one, with my thoughts about debugging. I hope they help!

1.8  Exercises

Exercise 2   Use a web browser to go to the Python website python.org. This page contains information about Python and links to Python-related pages, and it gives you the ability to search the Python documentation.

For example, if you enter print in the search window, the first link that appears is the documentation of the print statement. At this point, not all of it will make sense to you, but it is good to know where it is.

Exercise 3   Start the Python interpreter and type help() to start the online help utility. Or you can type help('print') to get information about the print statement.

If this example doesn’t work, you may need to install additional Python documentation or set an environment variable; the details depend on your operating system and version of Python.

Exercise 4   Start the Python interpreter and use it as a calculator. Python’s syntax for math operations is almost the same as standard mathematical notation. For example, the symbols +, - and / denote addition, subtraction and division, as you would expect. The symbol for multiplication is *.

If you run a 10 kilometer race in 43 minutes 30 seconds, what is your average time per mile? What is your average speed in miles per hour? (Hint: there are 1.61 kilometers in a mile).

1
This idiom means that someone realized something after a period of confusion.
2
In Python 3.0, print is a function, not a statement, so the syntax is print(’Hello, World!’). We will get to functions soon!
3
See Reeves and Nass, The Media Equation: How People Treat Computers, Television, and New Media Like Real People and Places.

2.3  Variable names and keywords

Programmers generally choose names for their variables that are meaningful—they document what the variable is used for.

Variable names can be arbitrarily long. They can contain both letters and numbers, but they have to begin with a letter. It is legal to use uppercase letters, but it is a good idea to begin variable names with a lowercase letter (you’ll see why later).

The underscore character (_) can appear in a name. It is often used in names with multiple words, such as my_name or airspeed_of_unladen_swallow.

If you give a variable an illegal name, you get a syntax error:

>>> 76trombones = 'big parade'
SyntaxError: invalid syntax
>>> more@ = 1000000
SyntaxError: invalid syntax
>>> class = 'Advanced Theoretical Zymurgy'
SyntaxError: invalid syntax

76trombones is illegal because it does not begin with a letter. more@ is illegal because it contains an illegal character, @. But what’s wrong with class?

It turns out that class is one of Python’s keywords. The interpreter uses keywords to recognize the structure of the program, and they cannot be used as variable names.

Python has 31 keywords1:

and       del       from      not       while    
as        elif      global    or        with     
assert    else      if        pass      yield    
break     except    import    print              
class     exec      in        raise              
continue  finally   is        return             
def       for       lambda    try

You might want to keep this list handy. If the interpreter complains about one of your variable names and you don’t know why, see if it is on this list.

2.9  Comments

As programs get bigger and more complicated, they get more difficult to read. Formal languages are dense, and it is often difficult to look at a piece of code and figure out what it is doing, or why.

For this reason, it is a good idea to add notes to your programs to explain in natural language what the program is doing. These notes are called comments, and they start with the # symbol:

# compute the percentage of the hour that has elapsed
percentage = (minute * 100) / 60

In this case, the comment appears on a line by itself. You can also put comments at the end of a line:

percentage = (minute * 100) / 60     # percentage of an hour

Everything from the # to the end of the line is ignored—it has no effect on the program.

Comments are most useful when they document non-obvious features of the code. It is reasonable to assume that the reader can figure out what the code does; it is much more useful to explain why.

This comment is redundant with the code and useless:

v = 5     # assign 5 to v

This comment contains useful information that is not in the code:

v = 5     # velocity in meters/second. 

Good variable names can reduce the need for comments, but long names can make complex expressions hard to read, so there is a tradeoff.

3.5  Adding new functions

So far, we have only been using the functions that come with Python, but it is also possible to add new functions. A function definition specifies the name of a new function and the sequence of statements that execute when the function is called.

Here is an example:

def print_lyrics():
    print "I'm a lumberjack, and I'm okay."
    print "I sleep all night and I work all day."

def is a keyword that indicates that this is a function definition. The name of the function is print_lyrics. The rules for function names are the same as for variable names: letters, numbers and some punctuation marks are legal, but the first character can’t be a number. You can’t use a keyword as the name of a function, and you should avoid having a variable and a function with the same name.

The empty parentheses after the name indicate that this function doesn’t take any arguments.

The first line of the function definition is called the header; the rest is called the body. The header has to end with a colon and the body has to be indented. By convention, the indentation is always four spaces (see Section 3.13). The body can contain any number of statements.

The strings in the print statements are enclosed in double quotes. Single quotes and double quotes do the same thing; most people use single quotes except in cases like this where a single quote (which is also an apostrophe) appears in the string.

If you type a function definition in interactive mode, the interpreter prints ellipses (...) to let you know that the definition isn’t complete:

>>> def print_lyrics():
...     print "I'm a lumberjack, and I'm okay."
...     print "I sleep all night and I work all day."
...

To end the function, you have to enter an empty line (this is not necessary in a script).

Defining a function creates a variable with the same name.

>>> print print_lyrics
<function print_lyrics at 0xb7e99e9c>
>>> print type(print_lyrics)
<type 'function'>

The value of print_lyrics is a function object, which has type 'function'.

The syntax for calling the new function is the same as for built-in functions:

>>> print_lyrics()
I'm a lumberjack, and I'm okay.
I sleep all night and I work all day.

Once you have defined a function, you can use it inside another function. For example, to repeat the previous refrain, we could write a function called repeat_lyrics:

def repeat_lyrics():
    print_lyrics()
    print_lyrics()

And then call repeat_lyrics:

>>> repeat_lyrics()
I'm a lumberjack, and I'm okay.
I sleep all night and I work all day.
I'm a lumberjack, and I'm okay.
I sleep all night and I work all day.

But that’s not really how the song goes.

3.7  Flow of execution

In order to ensure that a function is defined before its first use, you have to know the order in which statements are executed, which is called the flow of execution.

Execution always begins at the first statement of the program. Statements are executed one at a time, in order from top to bottom.

Function definitions do not alter the flow of execution of the program, but remember that statements inside the function are not executed until the function is called.

A function call is like a detour in the flow of execution. Instead of going to the next statement, the flow jumps to the body of the function, executes all the statements there, and then comes back to pick up where it left off.

That sounds simple enough, until you remember that one function can call another. While in the middle of one function, the program might have to execute the statements in another function. But while executing that new function, the program might have to execute yet another function!

Fortunately, Python is good at keeping track of where it is, so each time a function completes, the program picks up where it left off in the function that called it. When it gets to the end of the program, it terminates.

What’s the moral of this sordid tale? When you read a program, you don’t always want to read from top to bottom. Sometimes it makes more sense if you follow the flow of execution.

3.8  Parameters and arguments

Some of the built-in functions we have seen require arguments. For example, when you call math.sin you pass a number as an argument. Some functions take more than one argument: math.pow takes two, the base and the exponent.

Inside the function, the arguments are assigned to variables called parameters. Here is an example of a user-defined function that takes an argument:

def print_twice(bruce):
    print bruce
    print bruce

This function assigns the argument to a parameter named bruce. When the function is called, it prints the value of the parameter (whatever it is) twice.

This function works with any value that can be printed.

>>> print_twice('Spam')
Spam
Spam
>>> print_twice(17)
17
17
>>> print_twice(math.pi)
3.14159265359
3.14159265359

The same rules of composition that apply to built-in functions also apply to user-defined functions, so we can use any kind of expression as an argument for print_twice:

>>> print_twice('Spam '*4)
Spam Spam Spam Spam
Spam Spam Spam Spam
>>> print_twice(math.cos(math.pi))
-1.0
-1.0

The argument is evaluated before the function is called, so in the examples the expressions 'Spam '*4 and math.cos(math.pi) are only evaluated once.

You can also use a variable as an argument:

>>> michael = 'Eric, the half a bee.'
>>> print_twice(michael)
Eric, the half a bee.
Eric, the half a bee.

The name of the variable we pass as an argument (michael) has nothing to do with the name of the parameter (bruce). It doesn’t matter what the value was called back home (in the caller); here in print_twice, we call everybody bruce.

4.3  Exercises

The following is a series of exercises using TurtleWorld. They are meant to be fun, but they have a point, too. While you are working on them, think about what the point is.

The following sections have solutions to the exercises, so don’t look until you have finished (or at least tried).

Write a function called square that takes a parameter named t, which is a turtle. It should use the turtle to draw a square.

Write a function call that passes bob as an argument to square, and then run the program again.

Add another parameter, named length, to square. Modify the body so length of the sides is length, and then modify the function call to provide a second argument. Run the program again. Test your program with a range of values for length.
The functions lt and rt make 90-degree turns by default, but you can provide a second argument that specifies the number of degrees. For example, lt(bob, 45) turns bob 45 degrees to the left.

Make a copy of square and change the name to polygon. Add another parameter named n and modify the body so it draws an n-sided regular polygon. Hint: The exterior angles of an n-sided regular polygon are 360.0 / n degrees.

Write a function called circle that takes a turtle, t, and radius, r, as parameters and that draws an approximate circle by invoking polygon with an appropriate length and number of sides. Test your function with a range of values of r.

Hint: figure out the circumference of the circle and make sure that length * n = circumference.

Another hint: if bob is too slow for you, you can speed him up by changing bob.delay, which is the time between moves, in seconds. bob.delay = 0.01 ought to get him moving.

Make a more general version of circle called arc that takes an additional parameter angle, which determines what fraction of a circle to draw. angle is in units of degrees, so when angle=360, arc should draw a complete circle.

4.9  docstring

A docstring is a string at the beginning of a function that explains the interface (“doc” is short for “documentation”). Here is an example:

def polyline(t, n, length, angle):
    """Draw n line segments with the given length and
    angle (in degrees) between them.  t is a turtle.
    """    
    for i in range(n):
        fd(t, length)
        lt(t, angle)

This docstring is a triple-quoted string, also known as a multiline string because the triple quotes allow the string to span more than one line.

It is terse, but it contains the essential information someone would need to use this function. It explains concisely what the function does (without getting into the details of how it does it). It explains what effect each parameter has on the behavior of the function and what type each parameter should be (if it is not obvious).

Writing this kind of documentation is an important part of interface design. A well-designed interface should be simple to explain; if you are having a hard time explaining one of your functions, that might be a sign that the interface could be improved.

5.7  Nested conditionals

One conditional can also be nested within another. We could have written the trichotomy example like this:

if x == y:
    print 'x and y are equal'
else:
    if x < y:
        print 'x is less than y'
    else:
        print 'x is greater than y'

The outer conditional contains two branches. The first branch contains a simple statement. The second branch contains another if statement, which has two branches of its own. Those two branches are both simple statements, although they could have been conditional statements as well.

Although the indentation of the statements makes the structure apparent, nested conditionals become difficult to read very quickly. In general, it is a good idea to avoid them when you can.

Logical operators often provide a way to simplify nested conditional statements. For example, we can rewrite the following code using a single conditional:

if 0 < x:
    if x < 10:
        print 'x is a positive single-digit number.'

The print statement is executed only if we make it past both conditionals, so we can get the same effect with the and operator:

if 0 < x and x < 10:
    print 'x is a positive single-digit number.'

5.11  Keyboard input

The programs we have written so far are a bit rude in the sense that they accept no input from the user. They just do the same thing every time.

Python provides a built-in function called raw_input that gets input from the keyboard1. When this function is called, the program stops and waits for the user to type something. When the user presses Return or Enter, the program resumes and raw_input returns what the user typed as a string.

>>> input = raw_input()
What are you waiting for?
>>> print input
What are you waiting for?

Before getting input from the user, it is a good idea to print a prompt telling the user what to input. raw_input can take a prompt as an argument:

>>> name = raw_input('What...is your name?\n')
What...is your name?
Arthur, King of the Britons!
>>> print name
Arthur, King of the Britons!

The sequence \n at the end of the prompt represents a newline, which is a special character that causes a line break. That’s why the user’s input appears below the prompt.

If you expect the user to type an integer, you can try to convert the return value to int:

>>> prompt = 'What...is the airspeed velocity of an unladen swallow?\n'
>>> speed = raw_input(prompt)
What...is the airspeed velocity of an unladen swallow?
17
>>> int(speed)
17

But if the user types something other than a string of digits, you get an error:

>>> speed = raw_input(prompt)
What...is the airspeed velocity of an unladen swallow?
What do you mean, an African or a European swallow?
>>> int(speed)
ValueError: invalid literal for int()

We will see how to handle this kind of error later.

5.12  Debugging

The traceback Python displays when an error occurs contains a lot of information, but it can be overwhelming, especially when there are many frames on the stack. The most useful parts are usually:

What kind of error it was, and
Where it occurred.

Syntax errors are usually easy to find, but there are a few gotchas. Whitespace errors can be tricky because spaces and tabs are invisible and we are used to ignoring them.

>>> x = 5
>>>  y = 6
  File "<stdin>", line 1
    y = 6
    ^
SyntaxError: invalid syntax

In this example, the problem is that the second line is indented by one space. But the error message points to y, which is misleading. In general, error messages indicate where the problem was discovered, but the actual error might be earlier in the code, sometimes on a previous line.

The same is true of runtime errors. Suppose you are trying to compute a signal-to-noise ratio in decibels. The formula is SNRdb = 10 log10 (Psignal / Pnoise). In Python, you might write something like this:

import math
signal_power = 9
noise_power = 10
ratio = signal_power / noise_power
decibels = 10 * math.log10(ratio)
print decibels

But when you run it, you get an error message2:

Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "snr.py", line 5, in ?
    decibels = 10 * math.log10(ratio)
OverflowError: math range error

The error message indicates line 5, but there is nothing wrong with that line. To find the real error, it might be useful to print the value of ratio, which turns out to be 0. The problem is in line 4, because dividing two integers does floor division. The solution is to represent signal power and noise power with floating-point values.

In general, error messages tell you where the problem was discovered, but that is often not where it was caused.

6.2  Incremental development

As you write larger functions, you might find yourself spending more time debugging.

To deal with increasingly complex programs, you might want to try a process called incremental development. The goal of incremental development is to avoid long debugging sessions by adding and testing only a small amount of code at a time.

As an example, suppose you want to find the distance between two points, given by the coordinates (x1, y1) and (x2, y2). By the Pythagorean theorem, the distance is:

distance =  | √ |

(x2 − x1)^2 + (y2 − y1)^2

The first step is to consider what a distance function should look like in Python. In other words, what are the inputs (parameters) and what is the output (return value)?

In this case, the inputs are two points, which you can represent using four numbers. The return value is the distance, which is a floating-point value.

Already you can write an outline of the function:

def distance(x1, y1, x2, y2):
    return 0.0

Obviously, this version doesn’t compute distances; it always returns zero. But it is syntactically correct, and it runs, which means that you can test it before you make it more complicated.

To test the new function, call it with sample arguments:

>>> distance(1, 2, 4, 6)
0.0

I chose these values so that the horizontal distance is 3 and the vertical distance is 4; that way, the result is 5 (the hypotenuse of a 3-4-5 triangle). When testing a function, it is useful to know the right answer.

At this point we have confirmed that the function is syntactically correct, and we can start adding code to the body. A reasonable next step is to find the differences x2 − x1 and y2 − y1. The next version stores those values in temporary variables and prints them.

def distance(x1, y1, x2, y2):
    dx = x2 - x1
    dy = y2 - y1
    print 'dx is', dx
    print 'dy is', dy
    return 0.0

If the function is working, it should display 'dx is 3' and ’dy is 4’. If so, we know that the function is getting the right arguments and performing the first computation correctly. If not, there are only a few lines to check.

Next we compute the sum of squares of dx and dy:

def distance(x1, y1, x2, y2):
    dx = x2 - x1
    dy = y2 - y1
    dsquared = dx**2 + dy**2
    print 'dsquared is: ', dsquared
    return 0.0

Again, you would run the program at this stage and check the output (which should be 25). Finally, you can use math.sqrt to compute and return the result:

def distance(x1, y1, x2, y2):
    dx = x2 - x1
    dy = y2 - y1
    dsquared = dx**2 + dy**2
    result = math.sqrt(dsquared)
    return result

If that works correctly, you are done. Otherwise, you might want to print the value of result before the return statement.

The final version of the function doesn’t display anything when it runs; it only returns a value. The print statements we wrote are useful for debugging, but once you get the function working, you should remove them. Code like that is called scaffolding because it is helpful for building the program but is not part of the final product.

When you start out, you should add only a line or two of code at a time. As you gain more experience, you might find yourself writing and debugging bigger chunks. Either way, incremental development can save you a lot of debugging time.

The key aspects of the process are:

Start with a working program and make small incremental changes. At any point, if there is an error, you should have a good idea where it is.
Use temporary variables to hold intermediate values so you can display and check them.
Once the program is working, you might want to remove some of the scaffolding or consolidate multiple statements into compound expressions, but only if it does not make the program difficult to read.

Exercise 2

Use incremental development to write a function called hypotenuse that returns the length of the hypotenuse of a right triangle given the lengths of the two legs as arguments. Record each stage of the development process as you go.

6.6  Leap of faith

Following the flow of execution is one way to read programs, but it can quickly become labyrinthine. An alternative is what I call the “leap of faith.” When you come to a function call, instead of following the flow of execution, you assume that the function works correctly and returns the right result.

In fact, you are already practicing this leap of faith when you use built-in functions. When you call math.cos or math.exp, you don’t examine the bodies of those functions. You just assume that they work because the people who wrote the built-in functions were good programmers.

The same is true when you call one of your own functions. For example, in Section 6.4, we wrote a function called is_divisible that determines whether one number is divisible by another. Once we have convinced ourselves that this function is correct—by examining the code and testing—we can use the function without looking at the body again.

The same is true of recursive programs. When you get to the recursive call, instead of following the flow of execution, you should assume that the recursive call works (yields the correct result) and then ask yourself, “Assuming that I can find the factorial of n−1, can I compute the factorial of n?” In this case, it is clear that you can, by multiplying by n.

Of course, it’s a bit strange to assume that the function works correctly when you haven’t finished writing it, but that’s why it’s called a leap of faith!

6.8  Checking types

What happens if we call factorial and give it 1.5 as an argument?

>>> factorial(1.5)
RuntimeError: Maximum recursion depth exceeded

It looks like an infinite recursion. But how can that be? There is a base case—when n == 0. But if n is not an integer, we can miss the base case and recurse forever.

In the first recursive call, the value of n is 0.5. In the next, it is -0.5. From there, it gets smaller (more negative), but it will never be 0.

We have two choices. We can try to generalize the factorial function to work with floating-point numbers, or we can make factorial check the type of its argument. The first option is called the gamma function2 and it’s a little beyond the scope of this book. So we’ll go for the second.

We can use the built-in function isinstance to verify the type of the argument. While we’re at it, we can also make sure the argument is positive:

def factorial (n):
    if not isinstance(n, int):
        print 'Factorial is only defined for integers.'
        return None
    elif n < 0:
        print 'Factorial is not defined for negative integers.'
        return None
    elif n == 0:
        return 1
    else:
        return n * factorial(n-1)

The first base case handles nonintegers; the second catches negative integers. In both cases, the program prints an error message and returns None to indicate that something went wrong:

>>> factorial('fred')
Factorial is only defined for integers.
None
>>> factorial(-2)
Factorial is not defined for negative integers.
None

If we get past both checks, then we know that n is positive or zero, so we can prove that the recursion terminates.

This program demonstrates a pattern sometimes called a guardian. The first two conditionals act as guardians, protecting the code that follows from values that might cause an error. The guardians make it possible to prove the correctness of the code.

6.9  Debugging

Breaking a large program into smaller functions creates natural checkpoints for debugging. If a function is not working, there are three possibilities to consider:

There is something wrong with the arguments the function is getting; a precondition is violated.
There is something wrong with the function; a postcondition is violated.
There is something wrong with the return value or the way it is being used.

To rule out the first possibility, you can add a print statement at the beginning of the function and display the values of the parameters (and maybe their types). Or you can write code that checks the preconditions explicitly.

If the parameters look good, add a print statement before each return statement that displays the return value. If possible, check the result by hand. Consider calling the function with values that make it easy to check the result (as in Section 6.2).

If the function seems to be working, look at the function call to make sure the return value is being used correctly (or used at all!).

Adding print statements at the beginning and end of a function can help make the flow of execution more visible. For example, here is a version of factorial with print statements:

def factorial(n):
    space = ' ' * (4 * n)
    print space, 'factorial', n
    if n == 0:
        print space, 'returning 1'
        return 1
    else:
        recurse = factorial(n-1)
        result = n * recurse
        print space, 'returning', result
        return result

space is a string of space characters that controls the indentation of the output. Here is the result of factorial(5) :

                     factorial 5
                 factorial 4
             factorial 3
         factorial 2
     factorial 1
 factorial 0
 returning 1
     returning 1
         returning 2
             returning 6
                 returning 24
                     returning 120

If you are confused about the flow of execution, this kind of output can be helpful. It takes some time to develop effective scaffolding, but a little bit of scaffolding can save a lot of debugging.

7.3  The while statement

Computers are often used to automate repetitive tasks. Repeating identical or similar tasks without making errors is something that computers do well and people do poorly.

We have seen two programs, countdown and print_n, that use recursion to perform repetition, which is also called iteration. Because iteration is so common, Python provides several language features to make it easier. One is the for statement we saw in Section 4.2. We’ll get back to that later.

Another is the while statement. Here is a version of countdown that uses a while statement:

def countdown(n):
    while n > 0:
        print n
        n = n-1
    print 'Blastoff!'

You can almost read the while statement as if it were English. It means, “While n is greater than 0, display the value of n and then reduce the value of n by 1. When you get to 0, display the word Blastoff!”

More formally, here is the flow of execution for a while statement:

Evaluate the condition, yielding True or False.
If the condition is false, exit the while statement and continue execution at the next statement.
If the condition is true, execute the body and then go back to step 1.

This type of flow is called a loop because the third step loops back around to the top.

The body of the loop should change the value of one or more variables so that eventually the condition becomes false and the loop terminates. Otherwise the loop will repeat forever, which is called an infinite loop. An endless source of amusement for computer scientists is the observation that the directions on shampoo, “Lather, rinse, repeat,” are an infinite loop.

In the case of countdown, we can prove that the loop terminates because we know that the value of n is finite, and we can see that the value of n gets smaller each time through the loop, so eventually we have to get to 0. In other cases, it is not so easy to tell:

def sequence(n):
    while n != 1:
        print n,
        if n%2 == 0:        # n is even
            n = n/2
        else:               # n is odd
            n = n*3+1

The condition for this loop is n != 1, so the loop will continue until n is 1, which makes the condition false.

Each time through the loop, the program outputs the value of n and then checks whether it is even or odd. If it is even, n is divided by 2. If it is odd, the value of n is replaced with n*3+1. For example, if the argument passed to sequence is 3, the resulting sequence is 3, 10, 5, 16, 8, 4, 2, 1.

Since n sometimes increases and sometimes decreases, there is no obvious proof that n will ever reach 1, or that the program terminates. For some particular values of n, we can prove termination. For example, if the starting value is a power of two, then the value of n will be even each time through the loop until it reaches 1. The previous example ends with such a sequence, starting with 16.

The hard question is whether we can prove that this program terminates for all positive values of n. So far1, no one has been able to prove it or disprove it!

Exercise 1   Rewrite the function print_n from Section 5.8 using iteration instead of recursion.

7.6  Algorithms

Newton’s method is an example of an algorithm: it is a mechanical process for solving a category of problems (in this case, computing square roots).

It is not easy to define an algorithm. It might help to start with something that is not an algorithm. When you learned to multiply single-digit numbers, you probably memorized the multiplication table. In effect, you memorized 100 specific solutions. That kind of knowledge is not algorithmic.

But if you were “lazy,” you probably cheated by learning a few tricks. For example, to find the product of n and 9, you can write n−1 as the first digit and 10−n as the second digit. This trick is a general solution for multiplying any single-digit number by 9. That’s an algorithm!

Similarly, the techniques you learned for addition with carrying, subtraction with borrowing, and long division are all algorithms. One of the characteristics of algorithms is that they do not require any intelligence to carry out. They are mechanical processes in which each step follows from the last according to a simple set of rules.

In my opinion, it is embarrassing that humans spend so much time in school learning to execute algorithms that, quite literally, require no intelligence.

On the other hand, the process of designing algorithms is interesting, intellectually challenging, and a central part of what we call programming.

Some of the things that people do naturally, without difficulty or conscious thought, are the hardest to express algorithmically. Understanding natural language is a good example. We all do it, but so far no one has been able to explain how we do it, at least not in the form of an algorithm.

7.7  Debugging

As you start writing bigger programs, you might find yourself spending more time debugging. More code means more chances to make an error and more place for bugs to hide.

One way to cut your debugging time is “debugging by bisection.” For example, if there are 100 lines in your program and you check them one at a time, it would take 100 steps.

Instead, try to break the problem in half. Look at the middle of the program, or near it, for an intermediate value you can check. Add a print statement (or something else that has a verifiable effect) and run the program.

If the mid-point check is incorrect, there must be a problem in the first half of the program. If it is correct, the problem is in the second half.

Every time you perform a check like this, you halve the number of lines you have to search. After six steps (which is fewer than 100), you would be down to one or two lines of code, at least in theory.

In practice it is not always clear what the “middle of the program” is and not always possible to check it. It doesn’t make sense to count lines and find the exact midpoint. Instead, think about places in the program where there might be errors and places where it is easy to put a check. Then choose a spot where you think the chances are about the same that the bug is before or after the check.

8.3  Traversal with a for loop

A lot of computations involve processing a string one character at a time. Often they start at the beginning, select each character in turn, do something to it, and continue until the end. This pattern of processing is called a traversal. One way to write a traversal is with a while loop:

index = 0
while index < len(fruit):
    letter = fruit[index]
    print letter
    index = index + 1

This loop traverses the string and displays each letter on a line by itself. The loop condition is index < len(fruit), so when index is equal to the length of the string, the condition is false, and the body of the loop is not executed. The last character accessed is the one with the index len(fruit)-1, which is the last character in the string.

Exercise 1   Write a function that takes a string as an argument and displays the letters backward, one per line.

Another way to write a traversal is with a for loop:

for char in fruit:
    print char

Each time through the loop, the next character in the string is assigned to the variable char. The loop continues until no characters are left.

The following example shows how to use concatenation (string addition) and a for loop to generate an abecedarian series (that is, in alphabetical order). In Robert McCloskey’s book Make Way for Ducklings, the names of the ducklings are Jack, Kack, Lack, Mack, Nack, Ouack, Pack, and Quack. This loop outputs these names in order:

prefixes = 'JKLMNOPQ'
suffix = 'ack'

for letter in prefixes:
    print letter + suffix

The output is:

Jack
Kack
Lack
Mack
Nack
Oack
Pack
Qack

Of course, that’s not quite right because “Ouack” and “Quack” are misspelled.

Exercise 2   Modify the program to fix this error.

8.13  Exercises

Exercise 9

A string slice can take a third index that specifies the “step size;” that is, the number of spaces between successive characters. A step size of 2 means every other character; 3 means every third, etc.

>>> fruit = 'banana'
>>> fruit[0:5:2]
'bnn'

A step size of -1 goes through the word backwards, so the slice [::-1] generates a reversed string.

Use this idiom to write a one-line version of is_palindrome from Exercise 6.6.

Exercise 10

Read the documentation of the string methods at docs.python.org/lib/string-methods.html. You might want to experiment with some of them to make sure you understand how they work. strip and replace are particularly useful.

The documentation uses a syntax that might be confusing. For example, in find(sub[, start[, end]]), the brackets indicate optional arguments. So sub is required, but start is optional, and if you include start, then end is optional.

Exercise 11   The following functions are all intended to check whether a string contains any lowercase letters, but at least some of them are wrong. For each function, describe what the function actually does (assuming that the parameter is a string).

def any_lowercase1(s):
    for c in s:
        if c.islower():
            return True
        else:
            return False

def any_lowercase2(s):
    for c in s:
        if 'c'.islower():
            return 'True'
        else:
            return 'False'

def any_lowercase3(s):
    for c in s:
        flag = c.islower()
    return flag

def any_lowercase4(s):
    flag = False
    for c in s:
        flag = flag or c.islower()
    return flag

def any_lowercase5(s):
    for c in s:
        if not c.islower():
            return False
    return True

Exercise 12

ROT13 is a weak form of encryption that involves “rotating” each letter in a word by 13 places1. To rotate a letter means to shift it through the alphabet, wrapping around to the beginning if necessary, so ’A’ shifted by 3 is ’D’ and ’Z’ shifted by 1 is ’A’.

Write a function called rotate_word that takes a string and an integer as parameters, and that returns a new string that contains the letters from the original string “rotated” by the given amount.

For example, “cheer” rotated by 7 is “jolly” and “melon” rotated by -10 is “cubed”.

You might want to use the built-in functions ord, which converts a character to a numeric code, and chr, which converts numeric codes to characters.

Potentially offensive jokes on the Internet are sometimes encoded in ROT13. If you are not easily offended, find and decode some of them.

1
See wikipedia.org/wiki/ROT13.

9.2  Exercises

There are solutions to these exercises in the next section. You should at least attempt each one before you read the solutions.

Exercise 2   In 1939 Ernest Vincent Wright published a 50,000 word novel called Gadsby that does not contain the letter “e.” Since “e” is the most common letter in English, that’s not easy to do.

In fact, it is difficult to construct a solitary thought without using that most common symbol. It is slow going at first, but with caution and hours of training you can gradually gain facility.

All right, I’ll stop now.

Write a function called has_no_e that returns True if the given word doesn’t have the letter “e” in it.

Modify your program from the previous section to print only the words that have no “e” and compute the percentage of the words in the list have no “e.”

Exercise 3   Write a function named avoids that takes a word and a string of forbidden letters, and that returns True if the word doesn’t use any of the forbidden letters.

Modify your program to prompt the user to enter a string of forbidden letters and then print the number of words that don’t contain any of them. Can you find a combination of 5 forbidden letters that excludes the smallest number of words?

Exercise 4   Write a function named uses_only that takes a word and a string of letters, and that returns True if the word contains only letters in the list. Can you make a sentence using only the letters acefhlo? Other than “Hoe alfalfa?”

Exercise 5   Write a function named uses_all that takes a word and a string of required letters, and that returns True if the word uses all the required letters at least once. How many words are there that use all the vowels aeiou? How about aeiouy?

Exercise 6   Write a function called is_abecedarian that returns True if the letters in a word appear in alphabetical order (double letters are ok). How many abecedarian words are there?

9.5  Debugging

Testing programs is hard. The functions in this chapter are relatively easy to test because you can check the results by hand. Even so, it is somewhere between difficult and impossible to choose a set of words that test for all possible errors.

Taking has_no_e as an example, there are two obvious cases to check: words that have an ’e’ should return False; words that don’t should return True. You should have no trouble coming up with one of each.

Within each case, there are some less obvious subcases. Among the words that have an “e,” you should test words with an “e” at the beginning, the end, and somewhere in the middle. You should test long words, short words, and very short words, like the empty string. The empty string is an example of a special case, which is one of the non-obvious cases where errors often lurk.

In addition to the test cases you generate, you can also test your program with a word list like words.txt. By scanning the output, you might be able to catch errors, but be careful: you might catch one kind of error (words that should not be included, but are) and not another (words that should be included, but aren’t).

In general, testing can help you find bugs, but it is not easy to generate a good set of test cases, and even if you do, you can’t be sure your program is correct.

According to a legendary computer scientist:

Program testing can be used to show the presence of bugs, but never to show their absence!

— Edsger W. Dijkstra

10.13  Debugging

Careless use of lists (and other mutable objects) can lead to long hours of debugging. Here are some common pitfalls and ways to avoid them:

Don’t forget that most list methods modify the argument and return None. This is the opposite of the string methods, which return a new string and leave the original alone.

If you are used to writing string code like this:

word = word.strip()

It is tempting to write list code like this:

t = t.sort()           # WRONG!

Because sort returns None, the next operation you perform with t is likely to fail.

Before using list methods and operators, you should read the documentation carefully and then test them in interactive mode. The methods and operators that lists share with other sequences (like strings) are documented at docs.python.org/lib/typesseq.html. The methods and operators that only apply to mutable sequences are documented at docs.python.org/lib/typesseq-mutable.html.

Pick an idiom and stick with it.

Part of the problem with lists is that there are too many ways to do things. For example, to remove an element from a list, you can use pop, remove, del, or even a slice assignment.

To add an element, you can use the append method or the + operator. Assuming that t is a list and x is a list element, these are right:

t.append(x)
t = t + [x]

And these are wrong:

t.append([x])          # WRONG!
t = t.append(x)        # WRONG!
t + [x]                # WRONG!
t = t + x              # WRONG!

Try out each of these examples in interactive mode to make sure you understand what they do. Notice that only the last one causes a runtime error; the other three are legal, but they do the wrong thing.

Make copies to avoid aliasing.

If you want to use a method like sort that modifies the argument, but you need to keep the original list as well, you can make a copy.

orig = t[:]
t.sort()

In this example you could also use the built-in function sorted, which returns a new, sorted list and leaves the original alone. But in that case you should avoid using sorted as a variable name!

11.1  Dictionary as a set of counters

Suppose you are given a string and you want to count how many times each letter appears. There are several ways you could do it:

You could create 26 variables, one for each letter of the alphabet. Then you could traverse the string and, for each character, increment the corresponding counter, probably using a chained conditional.
You could create a list with 26 elements. Then you could convert each character to a number (using the built-in function ord), use the number as an index into the list, and increment the appropriate counter.
You could create a dictionary with characters as keys and counters as the corresponding values. The first time you see a character, you would add an item to the dictionary. After that you would increment the value of an existing item.

Each of these options performs the same computation, but each of them implements that computation in a different way.

An implementation is a way of performing a computation; some implementations are better than others. For example, an advantage of the dictionary implementation is that we don’t have to know ahead of time which letters appear in the string and we only have to make room for the letters that do appear.

Here is what the code might look like:

def histogram(s):
    d = dict()
    for c in s:
        if c not in d:
            d[c] = 1
        else:
            d[c] += 1
    return d

The name of the function is histogram, which is a statistical term for a set of counters (or frequencies).

The first line of the function creates an empty dictionary. The for loop traverses the string. Each time through the loop, if the character c is not in the dictionary, we create a new item with key c and the initial value 1 (since we have seen this letter once). If c is already in the dictionary we increment d[c].

Here’s how it works:

>>> h = histogram('brontosaurus')
>>> print h
{'a': 1, 'b': 1, 'o': 2, 'n': 1, 's': 2, 'r': 2, 'u': 2, 't': 1}

The histogram indicates that the letters ’a’ and 'b' appear once; 'o' appears twice, and so on.

Exercise 2

Dictionaries have a method called get that takes a key and a default value. If the key appears in the dictionary, get returns the corresponding value; otherwise it returns the default value. For example:

>>> h = histogram('a')
>>> print h
{'a': 1}
>>> h.get('a', 0)
1
>>> h.get('b', 0)
0

Use get to write histogram more concisely. You should be able to eliminate the if statement.

11.3  Reverse lookup

Given a dictionary d and a key k, it is easy to find the corresponding value v = d[k]. This operation is called a lookup.

But what if you have v and you want to find k? You have two problems: first, there might be more than one key that maps to the value v. Depending on the application, you might be able to pick one, or you might have to make a list that contains all of them. Second, there is no simple syntax to do a reverse lookup; you have to search.

Here is a function that takes a value and returns the first key that maps to that value:

def reverse_lookup(d, v):
    for k in d:
        if d[k] == v:
            return k
    raise ValueError

This function is yet another example of the search pattern, but it uses a feature we haven’t seen before, raise. The raise statement causes an exception; in this case it causes a ValueError, which generally indicates that there is something wrong with the value of a parameter.

If we get to the end of the loop, that means v doesn’t appear in the dictionary as a value, so we raise an exception.

Here is an example of a successful reverse lookup:

>>> h = histogram('parrot')
>>> k = reverse_lookup(h, 2)
>>> print k
r

And an unsuccessful one:

>>> k = reverse_lookup(h, 3)
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in ?
  File "<stdin>", line 5, in reverse_lookup
ValueError

The result when you raise an exception is the same as when Python raises one: it prints a traceback and an error message.

The raise statement takes a detailed error message as an optional argument. For example:

>>> raise ValueError, 'value does not appear in the dictionary'
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in ?
ValueError: value does not appear in the dictionary

A reverse lookup is much slower than a forward lookup; if you have to do it often, or if the dictionary gets big, the performance of your program will suffer.

Exercise 4   Modify reverse_lookup so that it builds and returns a list of all keys that map to v, or an empty list if there are none.

11.6  Global variables

In the previous example, known is created outside the function, so it belongs to the special frame called __main__. Variables in __main__ are sometimes called global because they can be accessed from any function. Unlike local variables, which disappear when their function ends, global variables persist from one function call to the next.

It is common to use global variables for flags; that is, boolean variables that indicate (“flag”) whether a condition is true. For example, some programs use a flag named verbose to control the level of detail in the output:

verbose = True

def example1():
    if verbose:
        print 'Running example1'

If you try to reassign a global variable, you might be surprised. The following example is supposed to keep track of whether the function has been called:

been_called = False

def example2():
    been_called = True         # WRONG

But if you run it you will see that the value of been_called doesn’t change. The problem is that example2 creates a new local variable named been_called. The local variable goes away when the function ends, and has no effect on the global variable.

To reassign a global variable inside a function you have to declare the global variable before you use it:

been_called = False

def example2():
    global been_called 
    been_called = True

The global statement tells the interpreter something like, “In this function, when I say been_called, I mean the global variable; don’t create a local one.”

Here’s an example that tries to update a global variable:

count = 0

def example3():
    count = count + 1          # WRONG

If you run it you get:

UnboundLocalError: local variable 'count' referenced before assignment

Python assumes that count is local, which means that you are reading it before writing it. The solution, again, is to declare count global.

def example3():
    global count
    count += 1

If the global value is mutable, you can modify it without declaring it:

known = {0:0, 1:1}

def example4():
    known[2] = 1

So you can add, remove and replace elements of a global list or dictionary, but if you want to reassign the variable, you have to declare it:

def example5():
    global known
    known = dict()

11.8  Debugging

As you work with bigger datasets it can become unwieldy to debug by printing and checking data by hand. Here are some suggestions for debugging large datasets:

Scale down the input:
If possible, reduce the size of the dataset. For example if the program reads a text file, start with just the first 10 lines, or with the smallest example you can find. You can either edit the files themselves, or (better) modify the program so it reads only the first n lines.

If there is an error, you can reduce n to the smallest value that manifests the error, and then increase it gradually as you find and correct errors.

Check summaries and types:
Instead of printing and checking the entire dataset, consider printing summaries of the data: for example, the number of items in a dictionary or the total of a list of numbers.

A common cause of runtime errors is a value that is not the right type. For debugging this kind of error, it is often enough to print the type of a value.

Write self-checks:
Sometimes you can write code to check for errors automatically. For example, if you are computing the average of a list of numbers, you could check that the result is not greater than the largest element in the list or less than the smallest. This is called a “sanity check” because it detects results that are “insane.”

Another kind of check compares the results of two different computations to see if they are consistent. This is called a “consistency check.”

Pretty print the output:
Formatting debugging output can make it easier to spot an error. We saw an example in Section 6.9. The pprint module provides a pprint function that displays built-in types in a more human-readable format.

Again, time you spend building scaffolding can reduce the time you spend debugging.

12.8  Sequences of sequences

I have focused on lists of tuples, but almost all of the examples in this chapter also work with lists of lists, tuples of tuples, and tuples of lists. To avoid enumerating the possible combinations, it is sometimes easier to talk about sequences of sequences.

In many contexts, the different kinds of sequences (strings, lists and tuples) can be used interchangeably. So how and why do you choose one over the others?

To start with the obvious, strings are more limited than other sequences because the elements have to be characters. They are also immutable. If you need the ability to change the characters in a string (as opposed to creating a new string), you might want to use a list of characters instead.

Lists are more common than tuples, mostly because they are mutable. But there are a few cases where you might prefer tuples:

In some contexts, like a return statement, it is syntactically simpler to create a tuple than a list. In other contexts, you might prefer a list.
If you want to use a sequence as a dictionary key, you have to use an immutable type like a tuple or string.
If you are passing a sequence as an argument to a function, using tuples reduces the potential for unexpected behavior due to aliasing.

Because tuples are immutable, they don’t provide methods like sort and reverse, which modify existing lists. But Python provides the built-in functions sorted and reversed, which take any sequence as a parameter and return a new list with the same elements in a different order.

12.11  Exercises

Exercise 3   Write a function called most_frequent that takes a string and prints the letters in decreasing order of frequency. Find text samples from several different languages and see how letter frequency varies between languages. Compare your results with the tables at wikipedia.org/wiki/Letter_frequencies.

Exercise 4

More anagrams!

Write a program that reads a word list from a file (see Section 9.1) and prints all the sets of words that are anagrams.

Here is an example of what the output might look like:

['deltas', 'desalt', 'lasted', 'salted', 'slated', 'staled']
['retainers', 'ternaries']
['generating', 'greatening']
['resmelts', 'smelters', 'termless']

Hint: you might want to build a dictionary that maps from a set of letters to a list of words that can be spelled with those letters. The question is, how can you represent the set of letters in a way that can be used as a key?

Modify the previous program so that it prints the largest set of anagrams first, followed by the second largest set, and so on.

In Scrabble a “bingo” is when you play all seven tiles in your rack, along with a letter on the board, to form an eight-letter word. What set of 8 letters forms the most possible bingos? Hint: there are seven.

Two words form a “metathesis pair” if you can transform one into the other by swapping two letters3; for example, “converse” and “conserve.” Write a program that finds all of the metathesis pairs in the dictionary. Hint: don’t test all pairs of words, and don’t test all possible swaps.

You can download a solution from thinkpython.com/code/anagram_sets.py.

Exercise 5

Here’s another Car Talk Puzzler4:

What is the longest English word, that remains a valid English word, as you remove its letters one at a time?

Now, letters can be removed from either end, or the middle, but you can’t rearrange any of the letters. Every time you drop a letter, you wind up with another English word. If you do that, you’re eventually going to wind up with one letter and that too is going to be an English word—one that’s found in the dictionary. I want to know what’s the longest word and how many letters does it have?

I’m going to give you a little modest example: Sprite. Ok? You start off with sprite, you take a letter off, one from the interior of the word, take the r away, and we’re left with the word spite, then we take the e off the end, we’re left with spit, we take the s off, we’re left with pit, it, and I.

Write a program to find all words that can be reduced in this way, and then find the longest one.

This exercise is a little more challenging than most, so here are some suggestions:

You might want to write a function that takes a word and computes a list of all the words that can be formed by removing one letter. These are the “children” of the word.

Recursively, a word is reducible if any of its children are reducible. As a base case, you can consider the empty string reducible.
The wordlist I provided, words.txt, doesn’t contain single letter words. So you might want to add “I”, “a”, and the empty string.
To improve the performance of your program, you might want to memoize the words that are known to be reducible.

You can see my solution at thinkpython.com/code/reducible.py.

1
In Python 3.0, zip returns an iterator of tuples, but for most purposes, an iterator behaves like a list.
2
This behavior is slightly different in Python 3.0.
3
This exercise is inspired by an example at puzzlers.org.
4
www.cartalk.com/content/puzzler/transcripts/200651.

13.2  Random numbers

Given the same inputs, most computer programs generate the same outputs every time, so they are said to be deterministic. Determinism is usually a good thing, since we expect the same calculation to yield the same result. For some applications, though, we want the computer to be unpredictable. Games are an obvious example, but there are more.

Making a program truly nondeterministic turns out to be not so easy, but there are ways to make it at least seem nondeterministic. One of them is to use algorithms that generate pseudorandom numbers. Pseudorandom numbers are not truly random because they are generated by a deterministic computation, but just by looking at the numbers it is all but impossible to distinguish them from random.

The random module provides functions that generate pseudorandom numbers (which I will simply call “random” from here on).

The function random returns a random float between 0.0 and 1.0 (including 0.0 but not 1.0). Each time you call random, you get the next number in a long series. To see a sample, run this loop:

import random

for i in range(10):
    x = random.random()
    print x

The function randint takes parameters low and high and returns an integer between low and high (including both).

>>> random.randint(5, 10)
5
>>> random.randint(5, 10)
9

To choose an element from a sequence at random, you can use choice:

>>> t = [1, 2, 3]
>>> random.choice(t)
2
>>> random.choice(t)
3

The random module also provides functions to generate random values from continuous distributions including Gaussian, exponential, gamma, and a few more.

Exercise 5

Write a function named choose_from_hist that takes a histogram as defined in Section 11.1 and returns a random value from the histogram, chosen with probability in proportion to frequency. For example, for this histogram:

>>> t = ['a', 'a', 'b']
>>> h = histogram(t)
>>> print h
{'a': 2, 'b': 1}

your function should ’a’ with probability 2/3 and 'b' with probability 1/3.

13.8  Markov analysis

If you choose words from the book at random, you can get a sense of the vocabulary, you probably won’t get a sentence:

this the small regard harriet which knightley's it most things

A series of random words seldom makes sense because there is no relationship between successive words. For example, in a real sentence you would expect an article like “the” to be followed by an adjective or a noun, and probably not a verb or adverb.

One way to measure these kinds of relationships is Markov analysis1, which characterizes, for a given sequence of words, the probability of the word that comes next. For example, the song Eric, the Half a Bee begins:

Half a bee, philosophically,
Must, ipso facto, half not be.
But half the bee has got to be
Vis a vis, its entity. D’you see?

But can a bee be said to be
Or not to be an entire bee
When half the bee is not a bee
Due to some ancient injury?

In this text, the phrase “half the” is always followed by the word “bee,” but the phrase “the bee” might be followed by either “has” or “is”.

The result of Markov analysis is a mapping from each prefix (like “half the” and “the bee”) to all possible suffixes (like “has” and “is”).

Given this mapping, you can generate a random text by starting with any prefix and choosing at random from the possible suffixes. Next, you can combine the end of the prefix and the new suffix to form the next prefix, and repeat.

For example, if you start with the prefix “Half a,” then the next word has to be “bee,” because the prefix only appears once in the text. The next prefix is “a bee,” so the next suffix might be “philosophically,” “be” or “due.”

In this example the length of the prefix is always two, but you can do Markov analysis with any prefix length. The length of the prefix is called the “order” of the analysis.

Exercise 8   Markov analysis:

Write a program to read a text from a file and perform Markov analysis. The result should be a dictionary that maps from prefixes to a collection of possible suffixes. The collection might be a list, tuple, or dictionary; it is up to you to make an appropriate choice. You can test your program with prefix length two, but you should write the program in a way that makes it easy to try other lengths.
Add a function to the previous program to generate random text based on the Markov analysis. Here is an example from Emma with prefix length 2:

He was very clever, be it sweetness or be angry, ashamed or only amused, at such a stroke. She had never thought of Hannah till you were never meant for me?" "I cannot make speeches, Emma:" he soon cut it all himself.

For this example, I left the punctuation attached to the words. The result is almost syntactically correct, but not quite. Semantically, it almost makes sense, but not quite.

What happens if you increase the prefix length? Does the random text make more sense?

Once your program is working, you might want to try a mash-up: if you analyze text from two or more books, the random text you generate will blend the vocabulary and phrases from the sources in interesting ways.

13.9  Data structures

Using Markov analysis to generate random text is fun, but there is also a point to this exercise: data structure selection. In your solution to the previous exercises, you had to choose:

How to represent the prefixes.
How to represent the collection of possible suffixes.
How to represent the mapping from each prefix to the collection of possible suffixes.

Ok, the last one is the easy; the only mapping type we have seen is a dictionary, so it is the natural choice.

For the prefixes, the most obvious options are string, list of strings, or tuple of strings. For the suffixes, one option is a list; another is a histogram (dictionary).

How should you choose? The first step is to think about the operations you will need to implement for each data structure. For the prefixes, we need to be able to remove words from the beginning and add to the end. For example, if the current prefix is “Half a,” and the next word is “bee,” you need to be able to form the next prefix, “a bee.”

Your first choice might be a list, since it is easy to add and remove elements, but we also need to be able to use the prefixes as keys in a dictionary, so that rules out lists. With tuples, you can’t append or remove, but you can use the addition operator to form a new tuple:

def shift(prefix, word):
    return prefix[1:] + (word,)

shift takes a tuple of words, prefix, and a string, word, and forms a new tuple that has all the words in prefix except the first, and word added to the end.

For the collection of suffixes, the operations we need to perform include adding a new suffix (or increasing the frequency of an existing one), and choosing a random suffix.

Adding a new suffix is equally easy for the list implementation or the histogram. Choosing a random element from a list is easy; choosing from a histogram is harder to do efficiently (see Exercise 13.7).

So far we have been talking mostly about ease of implementation, but there are other factors to consider in choosing data structures. One is run time. Sometimes there is a theoretical reason to expect one data structure to be faster than other; for example, I mentioned that the in operator is faster for dictionaries than for lists, at least when the number of elements is large.

But often you don’t know ahead of time which implementation will be faster. One option is to implement both of them and see which is better. This approach is called benchmarking. A practical alternative is to choose the data structure that is easiest to implement, and then see if it is fast enough for the intended application. If so, there is no need to go on. If not, there are tools, like the profile module, that can identify the places in a program that take the most time.

The other factor to consider is storage space. For example, using a histogram for the collection of suffixes might take less space because you only have to store each word once, no matter how many times it appears in the text. In some cases, saving space can also make your program run faster, and in the extreme, your program might not run at all if you run out of memory. But for many applications, space is a secondary consideration after run time.

One final thought: in this discussion, I have implied that we should use one data structure for both analysis and generation. But since these are separate phases, it would also be possible to use one structure for analysis and then convert to another structure for generation. This would be a net win if the time saved during generation exceeded the time spent in conversion.

13.10  Debugging

When you are debugging a program, and especially if you are working on a hard bug, there are four things to try:

reading:
Examine your code, read it back to yourself, and check that it says what you meant to say.
running:
Experiment by making changes and running different versions. Often if you display the right thing at the right place in the program, the problem becomes obvious, but sometimes you have to spend some time to build scaffolding.
ruminating:
Take some time to think! What kind of error is it: syntax, runtime, semantic? What information can you get from the error messages, or from the output of the program? What kind of error could cause the problem you’re seeing? What did you change last, before the problem appeared?
retreating:
At some point, the best thing to do is back off, undoing recent changes, until you get back to a program that works and that you understand. Then you can start rebuilding.

Beginning programmers sometimes get stuck on one of these activities and forget the others. Each activity comes with its own failure mode.

For example, reading your code might help if the problem is a typographical error, but not if the problem is a conceptual misunderstanding. If you don’t understand what your program does, you can read it 100 times and never see the error, because the error is in your head.

Running experiments can help, especially if you run small, simple tests. But if you run experiments without thinking or reading your code, you might fall into a pattern I call “random walk programming,” which is the process of making random changes until the program does the right thing. Needless to say, random walk programming can take a long time.

You have to take time to think. Debugging is like an experimental science. You should have at least one hypothesis about what the problem is. If there are two or more possibilities, try to think of a test that would eliminate one of them.

Taking a break helps with the thinking. So does talking. If you explain the problem to someone else (or even yourself), you will sometimes find the answer before you finish asking the question.

But even the best debugging techniques will fail if there are too many errors, or if the code you are trying to fix is too big and complicated. Sometimes the best option is to retreat, simplifying the program until you get to something that works and that you understand.

Beginning programmers are often reluctant to retreat because they can’t stand to delete a line of code (even if it’s wrong). If it makes you feel better, copy your program into another file before you start stripping it down. Then you can paste the pieces back in a little bit at a time.

Finding a hard bug requires reading, running, ruminating, and sometimes retreating. If you get stuck on one of these activities, try the others.

14.3  Format operator

The argument of write has to be a string, so if we want to put other values in a file, we have to convert them to strings. The easiest way to do that is with str:

>>> x = 52
>>> f.write(str(x))

An alternative is to use the format operator, %. When applied to integers, % is the modulus operator. But when the first operand is a string, % is the format operator.

The first operand is the format string, which contains one or more format sequences, which specify how the second operand is formatted. The result is a string.

For example, the format sequence '%d' means that the second operand should be formatted as an integer (d stands for “decimal”):

>>> camels = 42
>>> '%d' % camels
'42'

The result is the string '42', which is not to be confused with the integer value 42.

A format sequence can appear anywhere in the string, so you can embed a value in a sentence:

>>> camels = 42
>>> 'I have spotted %d camels.' % camels
'I have spotted 42 camels.'

If there is more than one format sequence in the string, the second argument has to be a tuple. Each format sequence is matched with an element of the tuple, in order.

The following example uses '%d' to format an integer, '%g' to format a floating-point number (don’t ask why), and '%s' to format a string:

>>> 'In %d years I have spotted %g %s.' % (3, 0.1, 'camels')
'In 3 years I have spotted 0.1 camels.'

The number of elements in the tuple has to match the number of format sequences in the string. Also, the types of the elements have to match the format sequences:

>>> '%d %d %d' % (1, 2)
TypeError: not enough arguments for format string
>>> '%d' % 'dollars'
TypeError: illegal argument type for built-in operation

In the first example, there aren’t enough elements; in the second, the element is the wrong type.

The format operator is powerful, but it can be difficult to use. You can read more about it at docs.python.org/lib/typesseq-strings.html.

14.12  Exercises

Exercise 5

The urllib module provides methods for manipulating URLs and downloading information from the web. The following example downloads and prints a secret message from thinkpython.com:

import urllib

conn = urllib.urlopen('http://thinkpython.com/secret.html')
for line in conn.fp:
    print line.strip()

Run this code and follow the instructions you see there.

Exercise 6

In a large collection of MP3 files, there may be more than one copy of the same song, stored in different directories or with different file names. The goal of this exercise is to search for these duplicates.

Write a program that searches a directory and all of its subdirectories, recursively, and returns a list of complete paths for all files with a given suffix (like .mp3). Hint: os.path provides several useful functions for manipulating file and path names.

To recognize duplicates, you can use a hash function that reads the file and generates a short summary of the contents. For example, MD5 (Message-Digest algorithm 5) takes an arbitrarily-long “message” and returns a 128-bit “checksum.” The probability is very small that two files with different contents will return the same checksum.

You can read about MD5 at wikipedia.org/wiki/Md5. On a Unix system you can use the program md5sum and a pipe to compute checksums from Python.

Exercise 7

The Internet Movie Database (IMDb) is an online collection of information about movies. Their database is available in plain text format, so it is reasonably easy to read from Python. For this exercise, the files you need are actors.list.gz and actresses.list.gz; you can download them from www.imdb.com/interfaces#plain.

I have written a program that parses these files and splits them into actor names, movie titles, etc. You can download it from thinkpython.com/code/imdb.py.

If you run imdb.py as a script, it reads actors.list.gz and prints one actor-movie pair per line. Or, if you import imdb you can use the function process_file to, well, process the file. The arguments are a filename, a function object and an optional number of lines to process. Here is an example:

import imdb

def print_info(actor, date, title, role):
    print actor, date, title, role

imdb.process_file('actors.list.gz', print_info)

When you call process_file, it opens filename, reads the contents, and calls print_info once for each line in the file. print_info takes an actor, date, movie title and role as arguments and prints them.

Write a program that reads actors.list.gz and actresses.list.gz and uses shelve to build a database that maps from each actor to a list of his or her films.

Two actors are “costars” if they have been in at least one movie together. Process the database you built in the previous step and build a second database that maps from each actor to a list of his or her costars.

Write a program that can play the “Six Degrees of Kevin Bacon,” which you can read about at wikipedia.org/wiki/Six_Degrees_of_Kevin_Bacon. This problem is challenging because it requires you to find the shortest path in a graph. You can read about shortest path algorithms at wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortest_path_problem.

15.9  Exercises

Exercise 4

World.py, which is part of Swampy (see Chapter 4), contains a class definition for a user-defined type called World. You can import it like this:

from World import World

This version of the import statement imports the World class from the World module. The following code creates a World object and calls the mainloop method, which waits for the user.

world = World()
world.mainloop()

A window should appear with a title bar and an empty square. We will use this window to draw Points, Rectangles and other shapes. Add the following lines before calling mainloop and run the program again.

canvas = world.ca(width=500, height=500, background='white')
bbox = [[-150,-100], [150, 100]]
canvas.rectangle(bbox, outline='black', width=2, fill='green4')

You should see a green rectangle with a black outline. The first line creates a Canvas, which appears in the window as a white square. The Canvas object provides methods like rectangle for drawing various shapes.

bbox is a list of lists that represents the “bounding box” of the rectangle. The first pair of coordinates is the lower-left corner of the rectangle; the second pair is the upper-right corner.

You can draw a circle like this:

canvas.circle([-25,0], 70, outline=None, fill='red')

The first parameter is the coordinate pair for the center of the circle; the second parameter is the radius.

If you add this line to the program, the result should resemble the national flag of Bangladesh (see wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallery_of_sovereign-state_flags).

Write a function called draw_rectangle that takes a Canvas and a Rectangle as arguments and draws a representation of the Rectangle on the Canvas.
Add an attribute named color to your Rectangle objects and modify draw_rectangle so that it uses the color attribute as the fill color.
Write a function called draw_point that takes a Canvas and a Point as arguments and draws a representation of the Point on the Canvas.
Define a new class called Circle with appropriate attributes and instantiate a few Circle objects. Write a function called draw_circle that draws circles on the canvas.

Write a program that draws the national flag of the Czech Republic. Hint: you can draw a polygon like this:

points = [[-150,-100], [150, 100], [150, -100]]
canvas.polygon(points, fill='blue')

I have written a small program that lists the available colors; you can download it from thinkpython.com/code/color_list.py.

16.2  Pure functions

In the next few sections, we’ll write two functions that add time values. They demonstrate two kinds of functions: pure functions and modifiers. They also demonstrate a development plan I’ll call prototype and patch, which is a way of tackling a complex problem by starting with a simple prototype and incrementally dealing with the complications.

Here is a simple prototype of add_time:

def add_time(t1, t2):
    sum = Time()
    sum.hour = t1.hour + t2.hour
    sum.minute = t1.minute + t2.minute
    sum.second = t1.second + t2.second
    return sum

The function creates a new Time object, initializes its attributes, and returns a reference to the new object. This is called a pure function because it does not modify any of the objects passed to it as arguments and it has no effect, like displaying a value or getting user input, other than returning a value.

To test this function, I’ll create two Time objects: start contains the start time of a movie, like Monty Python and the Holy Grail, and duration contains the run time of the movie, which is one hour 35 minutes.

add_time figures out when the movie will be done.

>>> start = Time()
>>> start.hour = 9
>>> start.minute = 45
>>> start.second =  0

>>> duration = Time()
>>> duration.hour = 1
>>> duration.minute = 35
>>> duration.second = 0

>>> done = add_time(start, duration)
>>> print_time(done)
10:80:00

The result, 10:80:00 might not be what you were hoping for. The problem is that this function does not deal with cases where the number of seconds or minutes adds up to more than sixty. When that happens, we have to “carry” the extra seconds into the minute column or the extra minutes into the hour column.

Here’s an improved version:

def add_time(t1, t2):
    sum = Time()
    sum.hour = t1.hour + t2.hour
    sum.minute = t1.minute + t2.minute
    sum.second = t1.second + t2.second

    if sum.second >= 60:
        sum.second -= 60
        sum.minute += 1

    if sum.minute >= 60:
        sum.minute -= 60
        sum.hour += 1

    return sum

Although this function is correct, it is starting to get big. We will see a shorter alternative later.

16.3  Modifiers

Sometimes it is useful for a function to modify the objects it gets as parameters. In that case, the changes are visible to the caller. Functions that work this way are called modifiers.

increment, which adds a given number of seconds to a Time object, can be written naturally as a modifier. Here is a rough draft:

def increment(time, seconds):
    time.second += seconds

    if time.second >= 60:
        time.second -= 60
        time.minute += 1

    if time.minute >= 60:
        time.minute -= 60
        time.hour += 1

The first line performs the basic operation; the remainder deals with the special cases we saw before.

Is this function correct? What happens if the parameter seconds is much greater than sixty?

In that case, it is not enough to carry once; we have to keep doing it until time.second is less than sixty. One solution is to replace the if statements with while statements. That would make the function correct, but not very efficient.

Exercise 3   Write a correct version of increment that doesn’t contain any loops.

Anything that can be done with modifiers can also be done with pure functions. In fact, some programming languages only allow pure functions. There is some evidence that programs that use pure functions are faster to develop and less error-prone than programs that use modifiers. But modifiers are convenient at times, and functional programs tend to be less efficient.

In general, I recommend that you write pure functions whenever it is reasonable and resort to modifiers only if there is a compelling advantage. This approach might be called a functional programming style.

Exercise 4   Write a “pure” version of increment that creates and returns a new Time object rather than modifying the parameter.

16.4  Prototyping versus planning

The development plan I am demonstrating is called “prototype and patch.” For each function, I wrote a prototype that performed the basic calculation and then tested it, patching errors along the way.

This approach can be effective, especially if you don’t yet have a deep understanding of the problem. But incremental corrections can generate code that is unnecessarily complicated—since it deals with many special cases—and unreliable—since it is hard to know if you have found all the errors.

An alternative is planned development, in which high-level insight into the problem can make the programming much easier. In this case, the insight is that a Time object is really a three-digit number in base 60 (see wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexagesimal.)! The second attribute is the “ones column,” the minute attribute is the “sixties column,” and the hour attribute is the “thirty-six hundreds column.”

When we wrote add_time and increment, we were effectively doing addition in base 60, which is why we had to carry from one column to the next.

This observation suggests another approach to the whole problem—we can convert Time objects to integers and take advantage of the fact that the computer knows how to do integer arithmetic.

Here is a function that converts Times to integers:

def time_to_int(time):
    minutes = time.hour * 60 + time.minute
    seconds = minutes * 60 + time.second
    return seconds

And here is the function that converts integers to Times (recall that divmod divides the first argument by the second and returns the quotient and remainder as a tuple).

def int_to_time(seconds):
    time = Time()
    minutes, time.second = divmod(seconds, 60)
    time.hour, time.minute = divmod(minutes, 60)
    return time

You might have to think a bit, and run some tests, to convince yourself that these functions are correct. One way to test them is to check that time_to_int(int_to_time(x)) == x for many values of x. This is an example of a consistency check.

Once you are convinced they are correct, you can use them to rewrite add_time:

def add_time(t1, t2):
    seconds = time_to_int(t1) + time_to_int(t2)
    return int_to_time(seconds)

This version is shorter than the original, and easier to verify.

Exercise 5   Rewrite increment using time_to_int and int_to_time.

In some ways, converting from base 60 to base 10 and back is harder than just dealing with times. Base conversion is more abstract; our intuition for dealing with time values is better.

But if we have the insight to treat times as base 60 numbers and make the investment of writing the conversion functions (time_to_int and int_to_time), we get a program that is shorter, easier to read and debug, and more reliable.

It is also easier to add features later. For example, imagine subtracting two Times to find the duration between them. The naïve approach would be to implement subtraction with borrowing. Using the conversion functions would be easier and more likely to be correct.

Ironically, sometimes making a problem harder (or more general) makes it easier (because there are fewer special cases and fewer opportunities for error).

17.8  Type-based dispatch

In the previous section we added two Time objects, but you also might want to add an integer to a Time object. The following is a version of __add__ that checks the type of other and invokes either add_time or increment:

# inside class Time:

    def __add__(self, other):
        if isinstance(other, Time):
            return self.add_time(other)
        else:
            return self.increment(other)

    def add_time(self, other):
        seconds = self.time_to_int() + other.time_to_int()
        return int_to_time(seconds)

    def increment(self, seconds):
        seconds += self.time_to_int()
        return int_to_time(seconds)

The built-in function isinstance takes a value and a class object, and returns True if the value is an instance of the class.

If other is a Time object, __add__ invokes add_time. Otherwise it assumes that the parameter is a number and invokes increment. This operation is called a type-based dispatch because it dispatches the computation to different methods based on the type of the arguments.

Here are examples that use the + operator with different types:

>>> start = Time(9, 45)
>>> duration = Time(1, 35)
>>> print start + duration
11:20:00
>>> print start + 1337
10:07:17

Unfortunately, this implementation of addition is not commutative. If the integer is the first operand, you get

>>> print 1337 + start
TypeError: unsupported operand type(s) for +: 'int' and 'instance'

The problem is, instead of asking the Time object to add an integer, Python is asking an integer to add a Time object, and it doesn’t know how to do that. But there is a clever solution for this problem: the special method __radd__, which stands for “right-side add.” This method is invoked when a Time object appears on the right side of the + operator. Here’s the definition:

# inside class Time:

    def __radd__(self, other):
        return self.__add__(other)

And here’s how it’s used:

>>> print 1337 + start
10:07:17

Exercise 5   Write an add method for Points that works with either a Point object or a tuple:

If the second operand is a Point, the method should return a new Point whose x coordinate is the sum of the x coordinates of the operands, and likewise for the y coordinates.
If the second operand is a tuple, the method should add the first element of the tuple to the x coordinate and the second element to the y coordinate, and return a new Point with the result.

17.9  Polymorphism

Type-based dispatch is useful when it is necessary, but (fortunately) it is not always necessary. Often you can avoid it by writing functions that work correctly for arguments with different types.

Many of the functions we wrote for strings will actually work for any kind of sequence. For example, in Section 11.1 we used histogram to count the number of times each letter appears in a word.

def histogram(s):
    d = dict()
    for c in s:
        if c not in d:
            d[c] = 1
        else:
            d[c] = d[c]+1
    return d

This function also works for lists, tuples, and even dictionaries, as long as the elements of s are hashable, so they can be used as keys in d.

>>> t = ['spam', 'egg', 'spam', 'spam', 'bacon', 'spam']
>>> histogram(t)
{'bacon': 1, 'egg': 1, 'spam': 4}

Functions that can work with several types are called polymorphic. Polymorphism can facilitate code reuse. For example, the built-in function sum, which adds the elements of a sequence, works as long as the elements of the sequence support addition.

Since Time objects provide an add method, they work with sum:

>>> t1 = Time(7, 43)
>>> t2 = Time(7, 41)
>>> t3 = Time(7, 37)
>>> total = sum([t1, t2, t3])
>>> print total
23:01:00

In general, if all of the operations inside a function work with a given type, then the function works with that type.

The best kind of polymorphism is the unintentional kind, where you discover that a function you already wrote can be applied to a type you never planned for.

18.3  Comparing cards

For built-in types, there are relational operators (<, >, ==, etc.) that compare values and determine when one is greater than, less than, or equal to another. For user-defined types, we can override the behavior of the built-in operators by providing a method named __cmp__.

__cmp__ takes two parameters, self and other, and returns a positive number if the first object is greater, a negative number if the second object is greater, and 0 if they are equal to each other.

The correct ordering for cards is not obvious. For example, which is better, the 3 of Clubs or the 2 of Diamonds? One has a higher rank, but the other has a higher suit. In order to compare cards, you have to decide whether rank or suit is more important.

The answer might depend on what game you are playing, but to keep things simple, we’ll make the arbitrary choice that suit is more important, so all of the Spades outrank all of the Diamonds, and so on.

With that decided, we can write __cmp__:

# inside class Card:

    def __cmp__(self, other):
        # check the suits
        if self.suit > other.suit: return 1
        if self.suit < other.suit: return -1

        # suits are the same... check ranks
        if self.rank > other.rank: return 1
        if self.rank < other.rank: return -1

        # ranks are the same... it's a tie
        return 0    

You can write this more concisely using tuple comparison:

# inside class Card:

    def __cmp__(self, other):
        t1 = self.suit, self.rank
        t2 = other.suit, other.rank
        return cmp(t1, t2)

The built-in function cmp has the same interface as the method __cmp__: it takes two values and returns a positive number if the first is larger, a negative number if the second is larger, and 0 if they are equal.

Exercise 1   Write a __cmp__ method for Time objects. Hint: you can use tuple comparison, but you also might consider using integer subtraction.

18.7  Inheritance

The language feature most often associated with object-oriented programming is inheritance. Inheritance is the ability to define a new class that is a modified version of an existing class.

It is called “inheritance” because the new class inherits the methods of the existing class. Extending this metaphor, the existing class is called the parent and the new class is called the child.

As an example, let’s say we want a class to represent a “hand,” that is, the set of cards held by one player. A hand is similar to a deck: both are made up of a set of cards, and both require operations like adding and removing cards.

A hand is also different from a deck; there are operations we want for hands that don’t make sense for a deck. For example, in poker we might compare two hands to see which one wins. In bridge, we might compute a score for a hand in order to make a bid.

This relationship between classes—similar, but different—lends itself to inheritance.

The definition of a child class is like other class definitions, but the name of the parent class appears in parentheses:

class Hand(Deck):
    """represents a hand of playing cards"""

This definition indicates that Hand inherits from Deck; that means we can use methods like pop_card and add_card for Hands as well as Decks.

Hand also inherits __init__ from Deck, but it doesn’t really do what we want: instead of populating the hand with 52 new cards, the init method for Hands should initialize cards with an empty list.

If we provide an init method in the Hand class, it overrides the one in the Deck class:

# inside class Hand:

    def __init__(self, label=''):
        self.cards = []
        self.label = label

So when you create a Hand, Python invokes this init method:

>>> hand = Hand('new hand')
>>> print hand.cards
[]
>>> print hand.label
new hand

But the other methods are inherited from Deck, so we can use pop_card and add_card to deal a card:

>>> deck = Deck()
>>> card = deck.pop_card()
>>> hand.add_card(card)
>>> print hand
King of Spades

A natural next step is to encapsulate this code in a method called move_cards:

#inside class Deck:

    def move_cards(self, hand, num):
        for i in range(num):
            hand.add_card(self.pop_card())

move_cards takes two arguments, a Hand object and the number of cards to deal. It modifies both self and hand, and returns None.

In some games, cards are moved from one hand to another, or from a hand back to the deck. You can use move_cards for any of these operations: self can be either a Deck or a Hand, and hand, despite the name, can also be a Deck.

Exercise 3   Write a Deck method called deal_hands that takes two parameters, the number of hands and the number of cards per hand, and that creates new Hand objects, deals the appropriate number of cards per hand, and returns a list of Hand objects.

Inheritance is a useful feature. Some programs that would be repetitive without inheritance can be written more elegantly with it. Inheritance can facilitate code reuse, since you can customize the behavior of parent classes without having to modify them. In some cases, the inheritance structure reflects the natural structure of the problem, which makes the program easier to understand.

On the other hand, inheritance can make programs difficult to read. When a method is invoked, it is sometimes not clear where to find its definition. The relevant code may be scattered among several modules. Also, many of the things that can be done using inheritance can be done as well or better without it.

18.9  Debugging

Inheritance can make debugging a challenge because when you invoke a method on an object, you might not know which method will be invoked.

Suppose you are writing a function that works with Hand objects. You would like it to work with all kinds of Hands, like PokerHands, BridgeHands, etc. If you invoke a method like shuffle, you might get the one defined in Deck, but if any of the subclasses override this method, you’ll get that version instead.

Any time you are unsure about the flow of execution through your program, the simplest solution is to add print statements at the beginning of the relevant methods. If Deck.shuffle prints a message that says something like Running Deck.shuffle, then as the program runs it traces the flow of execution.

As an alternative, you could use this function, which takes an object and a method name (as a string) and returns the class that provides the definition of the method:

def find_defining_class(obj, meth_name):
    for ty in type(obj).mro():
        if meth_name in ty.__dict__:
            return ty

Here’s an example:

>>> hand = Hand()
>>> print find_defining_class(hand, 'shuffle')
<class 'Card.Deck'>

So the shuffle method for this Hand is the one in Deck.

find_defining_class uses the mro method to get the list of class objects (types) that will be searched for methods. “MRO” stands for “method resolution order.”

Here’s a program design suggestion: whenever you override a method, the interface of the new method should be the same as the old. It should take the same parameters, return the same type, and obey the same preconditions and postconditions. If you obey this rule, you will find that any function designed to work with an instance of a superclass, like a Deck, will also work with instances of subclasses like a Hand or PokerHand.

If you violate this rule, your code will collapse like (sorry) a house of cards.

19.2  Buttons and callbacks

The method bu creates a Button widget:

button = g.bu(text='Press me.')

The return value from bu is a Button object. The button that appears in the Frame is a graphical representation of this object; you can control the button by invoking methods on it.

bu takes up to 32 parameters that control the appearance and function of the button. These parameters are called options. Instead of providing values for all 32 options, you can use keyword arguments, like text='Press me.', to specify only the options you need and use the default values for the rest.

When you add a widget to the Frame, it gets “shrink-wrapped;” that is, the Frame shrinks to the size of the Button. If you add more widgets, the Frame grows to accommodate them.

The method la creates a Label widget:

label = g.la(text='Press the button.')

By default, Tkinter stacks the widgets top-to-bottom and centers them. We’ll see how to override that behavior soon.

If you press the button, you will see that it doesn’t do much. That’s because you haven’t “wired it up;” that is, you haven’t told it what to do!

The option that controls the behavior of a button is command. The value of command is a function that gets executed when the button is pressed. For example, here is a function that creates a new Label:

def make_label():
    g.la(text='Thank you.')

Now we can create a button with this function as its command:

button2 = g.bu(text='No, press me!', command=make_label)

When you press this button, it should execute make_label and a new label should appear.

The value of the command option is a function object, which is known as a callback because after you call bu to create the button, the flow of execution “calls back” when the user presses the button.

This kind of flow is characteristic of event-driven programming. User actions, like button presses and key strokes, are called events. In event-driven programming, the flow of execution is determined by user actions rather than by the programmer.

The challenge of event-driven programming is to construct a set of widgets and callbacks that work correctly (or at least generate appropriate error messages) for any sequence of user actions.

Exercise 1   Write a program that creates a GUI with a single button. When the button is pressed it should create a second button. When that button is pressed, it should create a label that says, “Nice job!”.

What happens if you press the buttons more than once? You can see my solution at thinkpython.com/code/button_demo.py

19.7  Menus and Callables

A Menubutton is a widget that looks like a button, but when pressed it pops up a menu. After the user selects an item, the menu disappears.

Here is code that creates a color selection Menubutton (you can download it from thinkpython.com/code/menubutton_demo.py):

g = Gui()
g.la('Select a color:')
colors = ['red', 'green', 'blue']
mb = g.mb(text=colors[0])

mb creates the Menubutton. Initially, the text on the button is the name of the default color. The following loop creates one menu item for each color:

for color in colors:
    g.mi(mb, text=color, command=Callable(set_color, color))

The first argument of mi is the Menubutton these items are associated with.

The command option is a Callable object, which is something new. So far we have seen functions and bound methods used as callbacks, which works fine if you don’t have to pass any arguments to the function. Otherwise you have to construct a Callable object that contains a function, like set_color, and its arguments, like color.

The Callable object stores a reference to the function and the arguments as attributes. Later, when the user clicks on a menu item, the callback calls the function and passes the stored arguments.

Here is what set_color might look like:

def set_color(color):
    mb.config(text=color)
    print color

When the user selects a menu item and set_color is called, it configures the Menubutton to display the newly-selected color. It also print the color; if you try this example, you can confirm that set_color is called when you select an item (and not called when you create the Callable object).

19.8  Binding

A binding is an association between a widget, an event and a callback: when an event (like a button press) happens on a widget, the callback is invoked.

Many widgets have default bindings. For example, when you press a button, the default binding changes the relief of the button to make it look depressed. When you release the button, the binding restores the appearance of the button and invokes the callback specified with the command option.

You can use the bind method to override these default bindings or to add new ones. For example, this code creates a binding for a canvas (you can download the code in this section from thinkpython.com/code/draggable_demo.py):

ca.bind('<ButtonPress-1>', make_circle)

The first argument is an event string; this event is triggered when the user presses the left mouse button. Other mouse events include ButtonMotion, ButtonRelease and Double-Button.

The second argument is an event handler. An event handler is a function or bound method, like a callback, but an important difference is that an event handler takes an Event object as a parameter. Here is an example:

def make_circle(event):
    pos = ca.canvas_coords([event.x, event.y])
    item = ca.circle(pos, 5, fill='red')

The Event object contains information about the type of event and details like the coordinates of the mouse pointer. In this example the information we need is the location of the mouse click. These values are in “pixel coordinates,” which are defined by the underlying graphical system. The method canvas_coords translates them to “Canvas coordinates,” which are compatible with Canvas methods like circle.

For Entry widgets, it is common to bind the <Return> event, which is triggered when the user presses the Return or Enter key. For example, the following code creates a Button and an Entry.

bu = g.bu('Make text item:', make_text)
en = g.en()
en.bind('<Return>', make_text)

make_text is called when the Button is pressed or when the user hits Return while typing in the Entry. To make this work, we need a function that can be called as a command (with no arguments) or as an event handler (with an Event as an argument):

def make_text(event=None):
    text = en.get()
    item = ca.text([0,0], text)

make_text gets the contents of the Entry and displays it as a Text item in the Canvas.

It is also possible to create bindings for Canvas items. The following is a class definition for Draggable, which is a child class of Item that provides bindings that implement drag-and-drop capability.

class Draggable(Item):

    def __init__(self, item):
        self.canvas = item.canvas
        self.tag = item.tag
        self.bind('<Button-3>', self.select)
        self.bind('<B3-Motion>', self.drag)
        self.bind('<Release-3>', self.drop)

The init method takes an Item as a parameter. It copies the attributes of the Item and then creates bindings for three events: a button press, button motion, and button release.

The event handler select stores the coordinates of the current event and the original color of the item, then changes the color to yellow:

    def select(self, event):
        self.dragx = event.x
        self.dragy = event.y

        self.fill = self.cget('fill')
        self.config(fill='yellow')

cget stands for “get configuration;” it takes the name of an option as a string and returns the current value of that option.

drag computes how far the object has moved relative to the starting place, updates the stored coordinates, and then moves the item.

    def drag(self, event):
        dx = event.x - self.dragx
        dy = event.y - self.dragy

        self.dragx = event.x
        self.dragy = event.y

        self.move(dx, dy)

This computation is done in pixel coordinates; there is no need to convert to Canvas coordinates.

Finally, drop restores the original color of the item:

    def drop(self, event):
        self.config(fill=self.fill)

You can use the Draggable class to add drag-and-drop capability to an existing item. For example, here is a modified version of make_circle that uses circle to create an Item and Draggable to make it draggable:

def make_circle(event):
    pos = ca.canvas_coords([event.x, event.y])
    item = ca.circle(pos, 5, fill='red')
    item = Draggable(item)

This example demonstrates one of the benefits of inheritance: you can modify the capabilities of a parent class without modifying its definition. This is particularly useful if you want to change behavior defined in a module you did not write.

19.9  Debugging

One of the challenges of GUI programming is keeping track of which things happen while the GUI is being built and which things happen later in response to user events.

For example, when you are setting up a callback, it is a common error to call the function rather than passing a reference to it:

def the_callback():
    print 'Called.'

g.bu(text='This is wrong!', command=the_callback())

If you run this code, you will see that it calls the_callback immediately, and then creates the button. When you press the button, it does nothing because the return value from the_callback is None. Usually you do not want to invoke a callback while you are setting up the GUI; it should only be invoked later in response to a user event.

Another challenge of GUI programming is that you don’t have control of the flow of execution. Which parts of the program execute and their order are determined by user actions. That means that you have to design your program to work correctly for any possible sequence of events.

For example, the GUI in Exercise 19.3 has two widgets: one creates a Circle item and the other changes the color of the Circle. If the user creates the circle and then changes its color, there’s no problem. But what if the user changes the color of a circle that doesn’t exist yet? Or creates more than one circle?

As the number of widgets grows, it is increasingly difficult to imagine all possible sequences of events. One way to manage this complexity is to encapsulate the state of the system in an object and then consider:

What are the possible states? In the Circle example, we might consider two states: before and after the user creates the first circle.
In each state, what events can occur? In the example, the user can press either of the buttons, or quit.
For each state-event pair, what is the desired outcome? Since there are two states and two buttons, there are four state-event pairs to consider.
What can cause a transition from one state to another? In this case, there is a transition when the user creates the first circle.

You might also find it useful to define, and check, invariants that should hold regardless of the sequence of events.

This approach to GUI programming can help you write correct code without taking the time to test every possible sequence of user events!

19.11  Exercises

Exercise 4

For this exercise, you will write an image viewer. Here is a simple example:

g = Gui()
canvas = g.ca(width=300)
photo = PhotoImage(file='danger.gif')
canvas.image([0,0], image=photo)
g.mainloop()

PhotoImage reads a file and returns a PhotoImage object that Tkinter can display. Canvas.image puts the image on the canvas, centered on the given coordinates. You can also put images on labels, buttons, and some other widgets:

g.la(image=photo)
g.bu(image=photo)

PhotoImage can only handle a few image formats, like GIF and PPM, but we can use the Python Imaging Library (PIL) to read other files.

The name of the PIL module is Image, but Tkinter defines an object with the same name. To avoid the conflict, you can use import...as like this:

import Image as PIL
import ImageTk

The first line imports Image and gives it the local name PIL. The second line imports ImageTk, which can translate a PIL image into a Tkinter PhotoImage. Here’s an example:

image = PIL.open('allen.png')
photo2 = ImageTk.PhotoImage(image)
g.la(image=photo2)

Download image_demo.py, danger.gif and allen.png from thinkpython.com/code. Run image_demo.py. You might have to install PIL and ImageTk. They are probably in your software repository, but if not you can get them from pythonware.com/products/pil/.
In image_demo.py change the name of the second PhotoImage from photo2 to photo and run the program again. You should see the second PhotoImage but not the first.

The problem is that when you reassign photo it overwrites the reference to the first PhotoImage, which then disappears. The same thing happens if you assign a PhotoImage to a local variable; it disappears when the function ends.

To avoid this problem, you have to store a reference to each PhotoImage you want to keep. You can use a global variable, or store PhotoImages in a data structure or as an attribute of an object.

This behavior can be frustrating, which is why I am warning you (and why the example image says “Danger!”).

Starting with this example, write a program that takes the name of a directory and loops through all the files, displaying any files that PIL recognizes as images. You can use a try statement to catch the files PIL doesn’t recognize.

When the user clicks on the image, the program should display the next one.

PIL provides a variety of methods for manipulating images. You can read about them at pythonware.com/library/pil/handbook. As a challenge, choose a few of these methods and provide a GUI for applying them to images.

You can download a simple solution from thinkpython.com/code/ImageBrowser.py.

Exercise 5

A vector graphics editor is a program that allows users to draw and edit shapes on the screen and generate output files in vector graphics formats like Postscript and SVG1.

Write a simple vector graphics editor using Tkinter. At a minimum, it should allow users to draw lines, circles and rectangles, and it should use Canvas.dump to generate a Postscript description of the contents of the Canvas.

As a challenge, you could allow users to select and resize items on the Canvas.

Exercise 6

Use Tkinter to write a basic web browser. It should have a Text widget where the user can enter a URL and a Canvas to display the contents of the page.

You can use the urllib module to download files (see Exercise 14.5) and the HTMLParser module to parse the HTML tags (see docs.python.org/lib/module-HTMLParser.html).

At a minimum your browser should handle plain text and hyperlinks. As a challenge you could handle background colors, text formatting tags and images.

1
See wikipedia.org/wiki/Vector_graphics_editor.

A.1  Syntax errors

Syntax errors are usually easy to fix once you figure out what they are. Unfortunately, the error messages are often not helpful. The most common messages are SyntaxError: invalid syntax and SyntaxError: invalid token, neither of which is very informative.

On the other hand, the message does tell you where in the program the problem occurred. Actually, it tells you where Python noticed a problem, which is not necessarily where the error is. Sometimes the error is prior to the location of the error message, often on the preceding line.

If you are building the program incrementally, you should have a good idea about where the error is. It will be in the last line you added.

If you are copying code from a book, start by comparing your code to the book’s code very carefully. Check every character. At the same time, remember that the book might be wrong, so if you see something that looks like a syntax error, it might be.

Here are some ways to avoid the most common syntax errors:

Make sure you are not using a Python keyword for a variable name.

Check that you have a colon at the end of the header of every compound statement, including for, while, if, and def statements.

Make sure that any strings in the code have matching quotation marks.

If you have multiline strings with triple quotes (single or double), make sure you have terminated the string properly. An unterminated string may cause an invalid token error at the end of your program, or it may treat the following part of the program as a string until it comes to the next string. In the second case, it might not produce an error message at all!

An unclosed opening operator—(, {, or [—makes Python continue with the next line as part of the current statement. Generally, an error occurs almost immediately in the next line.
Check for the classic = instead of == inside a conditional.

Check the indentation to make sure it lines up the way it is supposed to. Python can handle space and tabs, but if you mix them it can cause problems. The best way to avoid this problem is to use a text editor that knows about Python and generates consistent indentation.

If nothing works, move on to the next section...

A.1.1  I keep making changes and it makes no difference.

If the interpreter says there is an error and you don’t see it, that might be because you and the interpreter are not looking at the same code. Check your programming environment to make sure that the program you are editing is the one Python is trying to run.

If you are not sure, try putting an obvious and deliberate syntax error at the beginning of the program. Now run it again. If the interpreter doesn’t find the new error, you are not running the new code.

There are a few likely culprits:

You edited the file and forgot to save the changes before running it again. Some programming environments do this for you, but some don’t.
You changed the name of the file, but you are still running the old name.
Something in your development environment is configured incorrectly.
If you are writing a module and using import, make sure you don’t give your module the same name as one of the standard Python modules.

If you are using import to read a module, remember that you have to restart the interpreter or use reload to read a modified file. If you import the module again, it doesn’t do anything.

If you get stuck and you can’t figure out what is going on, one approach is to start again with a new program like “Hello, World!,” and make sure you can get a known program to run. Then gradually add the pieces of the original program to the new one.

A.2  Runtime errors

Once your program is syntactically correct, Python can compile it and at least start running it. What could possibly go wrong?

A.2.1  My program does absolutely nothing.

This problem is most common when your file consists of functions and classes but does not actually invoke anything to start execution. This may be intentional if you only plan to import this module to supply classes and functions.

If it is not intentional, make sure that you are invoking a function to start execution, or execute one from the interactive prompt. Also see the “Flow of Execution” section below.

A.2.2  My program hangs.

If a program stops and seems to be doing nothing, it is “hanging.” Often that means that it is caught in an infinite loop or infinite recursion.

If there is a particular loop that you suspect is the problem, add a print statement immediately before the loop that says “entering the loop” and another immediately after that says “exiting the loop.”

Run the program. If you get the first message and not the second, you’ve got an infinite loop. Go to the “Infinite Loop” section below.

Most of the time, an infinite recursion will cause the program to run for a while and then produce a “RuntimeError: Maximum recursion depth exceeded” error. If that happens, go to the “Infinite Recursion” section below.

If you are not getting this error but you suspect there is a problem with a recursive method or function, you can still use the techniques in the “Infinite Recursion” section.

If neither of those steps works, start testing other loops and other recursive functions and methods.
If that doesn’t work, then it is possible that you don’t understand the flow of execution in your program. Go to the “Flow of Execution” section below.

Infinite Loop

If you think you have an infinite loop and you think you know what loop is causing the problem, add a print statement at the end of the loop that prints the values of the variables in the condition and the value of the condition.

For example:

while x > 0 and y < 0 :
    # do something to x
    # do something to y

    print  "x: ", x
    print  "y: ", y
    print  "condition: ", (x > 0 and y < 0)

Now when you run the program, you will see three lines of output for each time through the loop. The last time through the loop, the condition should be false. If the loop keeps going, you will be able to see the values of x and y, and you might figure out why they are not being updated correctly.

Infinite Recursion

Most of the time, an infinite recursion will cause the program to run for a while and then produce a Maximum recursion depth exceeded error.

If you suspect that a function or method is causing an infinite recursion, start by checking to make sure that there is a base case. In other words, there should be some condition that will cause the function or method to return without making a recursive invocation. If not, then you need to rethink the algorithm and identify a base case.

If there is a base case but the program doesn’t seem to be reaching it, add a print statement at the beginning of the function or method that prints the parameters. Now when you run the program, you will see a few lines of output every time the function or method is invoked, and you will see the parameters. If the parameters are not moving toward the base case, you will get some ideas about why not.

Flow of Execution

If you are not sure how the flow of execution is moving through your program, add print statements to the beginning of each function with a message like “entering function foo,” where foo is the name of the function.

Now when you run the program, it will print a trace of each function as it is invoked.

A.2.3  When I run the program I get an exception.

If something goes wrong during runtime, Python prints a message that includes the name of the exception, the line of the program where the problem occurred, and a traceback.

The traceback identifies the function that is currently running, and then the function that invoked it, and then the function that invoked that, and so on. In other words, it traces the sequence of function invocations that got you to where you are. It also includes the line number in your file where each of these calls occurs.

The first step is to examine the place in the program where the error occurred and see if you can figure out what happened. These are some of the most common runtime errors:

NameError:
You are trying to use a variable that doesn’t exist in the current environment. Remember that local variables are local. You cannot refer to them from outside the function where they are defined.

TypeError:
There are several possible causes:

You are trying to use a value improperly. Example: indexing a string, list, or tuple with something other than an integer.

There is a mismatch between the items in a format string and the items passed for conversion. This can happen if either the number of items does not match or an invalid conversion is called for.

You are passing the wrong number of arguments to a function or method. For methods, look at the method definition and check that the first parameter is self. Then look at the method invocation; make sure you are invoking the method on an object with the right type and providing the other arguments correctly.

KeyError:
You are trying to access an element of a dictionary using a key that the dictionary does not contain.

AttributeError:
You are trying to access an attribute or method that does not exist. Check the spelling! You can use dir to list the attributes that do exist.

If an AttributeError indicates that an object has NoneType, that means that it is None. One common cause is forgetting to return a value from a function; if you get to the end of a function without hitting a return statement, it returns None. Another common cause is using the result from a list method, like sort, that returns None.

IndexError:
The index you are using to access a list, string, or tuple is greater than its length minus one. Immediately before the site of the error, add a print statement to display the value of the index and the length of the array. Is the array the right size? Is the index the right value?

The Python debugger (pdb) is useful for tracking down Exceptions because it allows you to examine the state of the program immediately before the error. You can read about pdb at docs.python.org/lib/module-pdb.html.

A.2.4  I added so many print statements I get inundated with output.

One of the problems with using print statements for debugging is that you can end up buried in output. There are two ways to proceed: simplify the output or simplify the program.

To simplify the output, you can remove or comment out print statements that aren’t helping, or combine them, or format the output so it is easier to understand.

To simplify the program, there are several things you can do. First, scale down the problem the program is working on. For example, if you are searching a list, search a small list. If the program takes input from the user, give it the simplest input that causes the problem.

Second, clean up the program. Remove dead code and reorganize the program to make it as easy to read as possible. For example, if you suspect that the problem is in a deeply nested part of the program, try rewriting that part with simpler structure. If you suspect a large function, try splitting it into smaller functions and testing them separately.

Often the process of finding the minimal test case leads you to the bug. If you find that a program works in one situation but not in another, that gives you a clue about what is going on.

Similarly, rewriting a piece of code can help you find subtle bugs. If you make a change that you think shouldn’t affect the program, and it does, that can tip you off.

A.3  Semantic errors

In some ways, semantic errors are the hardest to debug, because the interpreter provides no information about what is wrong. Only you know what the program is supposed to do.

The first step is to make a connection between the program text and the behavior you are seeing. You need a hypothesis about what the program is actually doing. One of the things that makes that hard is that computers run so fast.

You will often wish that you could slow the program down to human speed, and with some debuggers you can. But the time it takes to insert a few well-placed print statements is often short compared to setting up the debugger, inserting and removing breakpoints, and “stepping” the program to where the error is occurring.

A.3.1  My program doesn’t work.

You should ask yourself these questions:

Is there something the program was supposed to do but which doesn’t seem to be happening? Find the section of the code that performs that function and make sure it is executing when you think it should.
Is something happening that shouldn’t? Find code in your program that performs that function and see if it is executing when it shouldn’t.
Is a section of code producing an effect that is not what you expected? Make sure that you understand the code in question, especially if it involves invocations to functions or methods in other Python modules. Read the documentation for the functions you invoke. Try them out by writing simple test cases and checking the results.

In order to program, you need to have a mental model of how programs work. If you write a program that doesn’t do what you expect, very often the problem is not in the program; it’s in your mental model.

The best way to correct your mental model is to break the program into its components (usually the functions and methods) and test each component independently. Once you find the discrepancy between your model and reality, you can solve the problem.

Of course, you should be building and testing components as you develop the program. If you encounter a problem, there should be only a small amount of new code that is not known to be correct.

A.3.2  I’ve got a big hairy expression and it doesn’t do what I expect.

Writing complex expressions is fine as long as they are readable, but they can be hard to debug. It is often a good idea to break a complex expression into a series of assignments to temporary variables.

For example:

self.hands[i].addCard(self.hands[self.findNeighbor(i)].popCard())

This can be rewritten as:

neighbor = self.findNeighbor(i)
pickedCard = self.hands[neighbor].popCard()
self.hands[i].addCard(pickedCard)

The explicit version is easier to read because the variable names provide additional documentation, and it is easier to debug because you can check the types of the intermediate variables and display their values.

Another problem that can occur with big expressions is that the order of evaluation may not be what you expect. For example, if you are translating the expression x/2 π into Python, you might write:

y = x / 2 * math.pi

That is not correct because multiplication and division have the same precedence and are evaluated from left to right. So this expression computes x π / 2.

A good way to debug expressions is to add parentheses to make the order of evaluation explicit:

 y = x / (2 * math.pi)

Whenever you are not sure of the order of evaluation, use parentheses. Not only will the program be correct (in the sense of doing what you intended), it will also be more readable for other people who haven’t memorized the rules of precedence.

A.3.3  I’ve got a function or method that doesn’t return what I expect.

If you have a return statement with a complex expression, you don’t have a chance to print the return value before returning. Again, you can use a temporary variable. For example, instead of:

return self.hands[i].removeMatches()

you could write:

count = self.hands[i].removeMatches()
return count

Now you have the opportunity to display the value of count before returning.

A.3.4  I’m really, really stuck and I need help.

First, try getting away from the computer for a few minutes. Computers emit waves that affect the brain, causing these symptoms:

Frustration and rage.

Superstitious beliefs (“the computer hates me”) and magical thinking (“the program only works when I wear my hat backward”).

Random walk programming (the attempt to program by writing every possible program and choosing the one that does the right thing).

If you find yourself suffering from any of these symptoms, get up and go for a walk. When you are calm, think about the program. What is it doing? What are some possible causes of that behavior? When was the last time you had a working program, and what did you do next?

Sometimes it just takes time to find a bug. I often find bugs when I am away from the computer and let my mind wander. Some of the best places to find bugs are trains, showers, and in bed, just before you fall asleep.

A.3.5  No, I really need help.

It happens. Even the best programmers occasionally get stuck. Sometimes you work on a program so long that you can’t see the error. A fresh pair of eyes is just the thing.

Before you bring someone else in, make sure you are prepared. Your program should be as simple as possible, and you should be working on the smallest input that causes the error. You should have print statements in the appropriate places (and the output they produce should be comprehensible). You should understand the problem well enough to describe it concisely.

When you bring someone in to help, be sure to give them the information they need:

If there is an error message, what is it and what part of the program does it indicate?
What was the last thing you did before this error occurred? What were the last lines of code that you wrote, or what is the new test case that fails?
What have you tried so far, and what have you learned?

When you find the bug, take a second to think about what you could have done to find it faster. Next time you see something similar, you will be able to find the bug more quickly.

Remember, the goal is not just to make the program work. The goal is to learn how to make the program work.